<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Euroclydon vvinde commanded to cease: or, A quenching of the fiery darts by Scripture-arguments, declarations, and visions. Being a moderate vindication of his Highness the Lord Protector, from the popular aspersions first accasioned [sic] against him by the malice of the Presbyterians, and now blown up by all parties. Also, something in behalfe of the desolate Church, and King Charles, which declares hopes of union between him and his Highness the Lord Protector, with an apology of the author concerning the year 1653. and many other things discovered. / By Arise Evans.</title>
            <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84152</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862435</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114594</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240952800</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1491_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201962</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862435</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862435e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 191:E1491[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Euroclydon vvinde commanded to cease: or, A quenching of the fiery darts by Scripture-arguments, declarations, and visions. Being a moderate vindication of his Highness the Lord Protector, from the popular aspersions first accasioned [sic] against him by the malice of the Presbyterians, and now blown up by all parties. Also, something in behalfe of the desolate Church, and King Charles, which declares hopes of union between him and his Highness the Lord Protector, with an apology of the author concerning the year 1653. and many other things discovered. / By Arise Evans.</title>
                  <author>Evans, Arise, b. 1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1653. But according to the mis-apprehension of the vulgar, 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Title page has Biblical citations in margin after lines 2 and 5.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 25".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114594:1"/>
            <p>The <hi>Euroclydon</hi> WINDE Commanded to cease:<note place="margin">Act. 27 14. Mark. 4.39.</note> OR, A quenching of the Fiery Darts by Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Arguments, Declarations,<note place="margin">Eph. 6.16.</note> and Visions.</p>
            <p>Being a moderate Vindication of his Highness the Lord Protector, from the popular asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions first accasioned against him by the malice of the Presbyterians, and now blown up by all patties.</p>
            <p>ALSO, Something in behalfe of the Desolate CHURCH, and King CHARLES, which declares hopes of Union between Him and his Highness the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, with an Apology of the Author con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the year 1653. and many other things discovered.</p>
            <p>By ARISE EVANS.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 22.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Thou shalt not raise nor receive a false Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port. Put not thine hand with the wicked to be an unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous witnesse.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Psal. 12.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> For the Oppression of the poore for the Sighing of the needy, now will I arise, saith the Lord, I will set him in safety from him that puffeth at him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for the Author, in the year 1653. But accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the mis-apprehension of the Vulgar, 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:114594:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114594:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Sall never be at <hi>rest</hi> untill time come againe that every one may <hi>sit under his Vine, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Fig-tree, and that there be none to make them afraid,</hi> Mich. 4.4. and that is for both Church and Kingdome to flourish againe, as it did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time: we have this note upon this businesse in the Scripture often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, lest we should forget it. Judges 17.6.18.1: 19.1.21.25. saith he, <hi>In those dayes when there was no King in Israel, every one did what was right in his owne eyes:</hi> and <hi>in those times,</hi> saith the Prophet <hi>Oded,</hi> 2 Chro. 15.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>There was no peace to him that went out, nor to him that came in, but great vexation was upon all the Inhabitants of the Country:</hi> but in the time of <hi>Solomon</hi> it was otherwayes, for it is said that <hi>Israel</hi> (then) did sit in peace, <hi>every one under his Vine, and under his Fig-tree.</hi> 1 Kings 4.24, 25. Here you see the different condition
<pb facs="tcp:114594:3"/> between them that have <hi>a Ring</hi> and them that have none. And <hi>Solomon</hi> was a man of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st, to give Rest unto <hi>Israel,</hi> and a Type of <hi>CHRIST JESƲS,</hi> and of a <hi>KING</hi> u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der him, that in the end of the world shall appeare and <hi>reigne</hi> over all the earth, to give Rest unto all nations, that there sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be no more warres, and that a man may travell safely though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the whole world, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.10 <hi>Za<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Isa.</hi> 2 4. <hi>Micha</hi> 43.4 For this <hi>KING</hi> shall settle one way of <hi>Gods worship</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> through out all the earth, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.16. and have his Deputy in all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>who shall rule in peace,</hi> and give Him account of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their actions; neither shall any among them strive about title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for the sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rit of Ambition shall be taken away; <hi>but all shall submit to him:</hi> and this is the <hi>rest</hi> which <hi>God</hi> will bring men unto here <hi>on earth,</hi> and that <hi>death</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght be <hi>destroyed,</hi> that is, they shall not envie and destroy one another any <hi>more.</hi> And now the end wherefore I take this ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n me, is for to reconcile these parties who are most concerned in this foresaid work of God, nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, His M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>j sty <hi>K. CHARLES.</hi> &amp; his Highness <hi>OLIVER</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Prot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctor, whom I believe upon good grounds, in the next generation, will
<pb facs="tcp:114594:3"/> meet in one <hi>person</hi> that shall further eff ct <hi>the same worke of God.</hi> Therefore having <hi>visions</hi> and <hi>Revelations</hi> tending to that <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious union</hi> which shall not be, <hi>I hope,</hi> in the power of any Creature to <hi>hinder,</hi> It being <hi>Gods</hi> purpose and designe, <hi>I am bound in Conscience</hi> to declare the truth of God concerning the <hi>same,</hi> with that power and so <hi>cleare,</hi> that shall bring it to <hi>effect,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing assured <hi>GODS PRESENCE</hi> goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it.</p>
            <p>Some say the <hi>Starres</hi> or planets, are <hi>signes</hi> of the times <hi>that declare things to come.</hi> And that they doe not only <hi>declare,</hi> but have also a power in them by their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,</hi> to bring what they <hi>declare to passe.</hi> I wish it were so with me in this <hi>matter.</hi> That I might <hi>not only declare it,</hi> but be also instrumental under <hi>God</hi> to bring it to pass; and that though I was but passive when I declared the troubles of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdome</hi> that came upon us, since my suffering in 1638. <hi>which troubles,</hi> I was in no way <hi>active</hi> to bring it to passe; yet I shall endeavour, <hi>God helping me,</hi> with all my might, to end these troubles, and act to take away the confused darknesse too too rife among us, by shewing the light of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> that is, not onely in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie <hi>King Charles,</hi> but also in his Highnesse
<pb facs="tcp:114594:4"/>
               <hi>Oliver Protector,</hi> who are the two golden <hi>Pipes</hi> which empty the golden <hi>Oyle</hi> out of themselves; or the two <hi>ANOINTED</hi> Ones, that stand by the power of our <hi>LORD JESƲS,</hi> and are appointed to bring all nations to a perfect Rest, <hi>Zach.</hi> 4.12.14. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. and as <hi>Israel</hi> was gone to such a height of confusion <hi>for want of a King to rule them,</hi> according to the Law of <hi>God,</hi> prescribed and delivered to them by their <hi>Predecessors,</hi> to walk by the <hi>light</hi> thereof, did in their actions exceed the <hi>Sodomits</hi> with such <hi>violence and filthinesse,</hi> that none could travell among them in safety, <hi>Judg.</hi> 19. <hi>Judg.</hi> 20. and what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the destruction of above seventy thousand in one week, besides women and children.</p>
            <p>So in like manner <hi>or worse;</hi> now we have a generation among us that hath the like spirit of <hi>Sodomi,</hi> who make but a mock of <hi>sinne,</hi> and count men foolish because they believe the <hi>Ministers</hi> and the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> that tells them of <hi>sinne;</hi> and though they will use the <hi>Scripture</hi> sometimes to maintaine their wickednesse, yet they doe it from a <hi>conceit</hi> they have, <hi>thinking to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it by it selfe,</hi> as if a man, out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice against fire, <hi>should conclude thus, saying,</hi> I shall not be able to destroy this creature
<pb facs="tcp:114594:4"/> (Fire) no other way than by burning all things with it, that may shew it and keepe it alive: and they have such a delight to do evill, that they glory in nothing more than in destroying all <hi>Ministers,</hi> all <hi>Lawes,</hi> all <hi>Beliefs</hi> in any thing delivered from <hi>God</hi> by our <hi>Predecessors</hi> to us; neither are they able to teach men any thing, except to shew them how they shall doe to bring themselves <hi>(in time)</hi> to be more bruitish, and void of <hi>God</hi> and of Reason, than the worser sort of Beasts:</p>
            <p>In this condition doth <hi>our Land languish, ready to give up the ghost,</hi> therefore is it not <hi>time</hi> to comfort her, and to give her to understand her nakednesse, and to shew her from whence she is fallen, that she may <hi>repent:</hi> And because of this, what man that hath the spirit of God, can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to speak those things that pertaine to the glory of God, and the good of his People? For I am confident (once) <hi>all England</hi> did engage themselves to serve the Lord, and to worship him according to his Truth established among us.</p>
            <p>What is Man more than a Beast, if he hath not the grace of God to rule him? By his owne nature he is worse than the worser kinde of Beasts; for no sort of Beasts will prey and feede upon his owne
<pb facs="tcp:114594:5"/> Kinde, if he can forbeare it; but man is of that nature, that when he may have other Creatures to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed upon, he to choose, will feed upon mans flesh; witnesse those wild men called <hi>Caniballs, that doe so;</hi> and there is no difference in nature betweene any nation and them; but as the measure <hi>of the grace of God</hi> hath separated us, so that if <hi>God</hi> did but withdraw his <hi>graces</hi> from this Nation of <hi>England,</hi> and that we shou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d leave the wisdome of our <hi>Predecessors,</hi> as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did, that now are turned <hi>Cani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls,</hi> for they are supposed to be of that Nation, and be left to our owne lust, we should soon become such as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are.</p>
            <p>Why then should we sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght Learning, and gifts of Tongues <hi>(which by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence doth preserve us)</hi> no more now than the <hi>Apostles did;</hi> for if they being <hi>unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> to fit and enable them for the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strie,</hi> did rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve those gifts <hi>miraculously:</hi> Is <hi>learning</hi> now the worse, <hi>because</hi> men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to it in an ordinary <hi>way?</hi> Doth not that <hi>miraculous</hi> descending of <hi>learning</hi> and tongues upon the <hi>Apostles, Acts</hi> 1 4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7.8.11. shew us what need we have of it: And doth it not also shew us, that <hi>Learning</hi> is not from <hi>beneath,</hi> but comes from <hi>above?</hi> And that whether we have it in an ordinary way, <hi>as S. Paul had
<pb facs="tcp:114594:5"/> it,</hi> or in an extraordinary way, <hi>it is the same gift of God;</hi> And who was more <hi>excellent</hi> among the Apostles <hi>than S. Paul was?</hi> or more <hi>learned?</hi> Acts 26.24. 1 Cor. 14.18. But he had it not miraculously, <hi>for he needed it not so,</hi> because he was a <hi>learned</hi> man before▪ brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let us not loath <hi>Learning,</hi> as the <hi>Israelites</hi> loathed the <hi>Manna,</hi> Numb. 11.5, 6. because it was now so <hi>common,</hi> for we cannot live the life of Christians <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it;</hi> and though many have <hi>Learning</hi> and abuse it, as they abuse the other gifts of God, yet <hi>Learning</hi> in it selfe is a <hi>super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall gift,</hi> which some cannot attain to, <hi>though</hi> they go to <hi>Schoole,</hi> and to all the <hi>Ʋniversities,</hi> and are <hi>wise</hi> in other things; for, <hi>saith he,</hi> it is a gift, <hi>The Lord God hath given me the Tongue of the Learned;</hi> and he counts it <hi>the prime gift of God,</hi> and that the humours of men, <hi>who</hi> are contrary to <hi>Learning,</hi> is but a <hi>fleshly lust,</hi> which as a <hi>fire</hi> will devoure them, so that <hi>they shall lie down in sorrow,</hi> as you may see <hi>Isa.</hi> 50.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>Jude</hi> 22.23.</p>
            <p>Therefore, I say, it is needfull for me to improve that little talent of <hi>Learning,</hi> which as a spark by the providence of God, <hi>descended upon me</hi> from the <hi>learned;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:114594:6"/> which if I should <hi>deny,</hi> I were a liar in it, without which <hi>Learning</hi> I were no more able to expresse <hi>my minde▪</hi> and to reveale the divine Mysteries of God (<hi>though I did understand them,</hi> Mat. 13.11.) than the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles were afore; they received it mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culously, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. and these oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers, like <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (Acts 8.9, 10, 11, 12, &amp;c.) had <hi>learning</hi> first from our <hi>Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors,</hi> else were they not so able to fight against it, <hi>and deny it</hi> with that power as they doe to their owne <hi>damnation:</hi> But I hope they will repent and returne to God.</p>
            <p>I labour in this little Book, as I have done in my former Books, to inform all men of the truth, that God may have the glory, and we the comfort of our salvation, and to enlighten mens understanding concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth of the <hi>Ch. of Engl.</hi> as it was established <hi>among us,</hi> and to <hi>vindicate</hi> his Highnesse the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aspersions falsly cast upon him, and to bring King <hi>Charles</hi> and him to unity and peace againe; for <hi>Charlemaine</hi> is that <hi>grain of Mustard-seed,</hi> Mark 4.30, 31, 32.</p>
            <p>And why am I so pestered with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at I cannot <hi>rest,</hi> but all the day long answer them? And why are my books gone over all the earth, and translated into all
<pb facs="tcp:114594:6"/> languages, and are so famous, that I am troubled to answer <hi>men</hi> that come from <hi>Turky,</hi> from <hi>Italy,</hi> from <hi>Germany,</hi> from <hi>Spain,</hi> yea, and from all parts of the <hi>world,</hi> where English men goe: Is it not because of the mighty great influence <hi>CHARLES STƲART</hi> hath upon the world? <hi>for I am confident,</hi> If I had declared as much as I did <hi>for any other man,</hi> it would not have been regarded at all; for though his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are beyond any <hi>mans,</hi> yet they make him more glorious, than if he had excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the greatest <hi>King</hi> on earth in prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and sets all to looke upon him as <hi>THE MAN,</hi> who by Gods providence is fitted and qualified by his afflictions, to be the most excellent <hi>Prince,</hi> worthy and able to enjoy the greatest Dominion, Pomp and Glory in the World, and not transgresse therein. And now the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants and Anabaptists seeing this, and presuming upon their strength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Army, <hi>give out,</hi> that they will declare for the <hi>King,</hi> and bring him in: and so do the levelling party <hi>give out,</hi> as if they would doe it, and the Presbyters too, all for their own ends; But I hope God will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the Army for to see that these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sputings, <hi>vaine jangling,</hi> and such fallacings, is but a <hi>fleshly lust that warres against the
<pb facs="tcp:114594:7"/> soule,</hi> and destroys it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> faith in God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.19.20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4.5. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16, 17, 18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 11. <hi>Jude</hi> 23. And <hi>Jude</hi> after he had sufficiently sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wed the abomination of this <hi>fleshly lust that warres against the soule,</hi> exhorteth us to help them that are troubled with that <hi>dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ase,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aying <hi>&amp; of some have compassion▪ m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king a diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rence, and others save, with feare pulling them out of the fire, hating even the garment spotted by the flesh.</hi> Jude 22.23.</p>
            <p>And the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also a fl shly <hi>lust</hi> that wars against the body of <hi>man,</hi> and destroyes it with a burning <hi>disease,</hi> called the <hi>Pox,</hi> which is too well known among us. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15, 16, 17, 18. yet many repent of that, &amp; their soules are saved: Bur this <hi>fleshly lust</hi> that warres against the soule, is more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, because it doth destroy the soule fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, <hi>and then</hi> destroyes the body; for Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter is a loading <hi>Card</hi> that brings women and men <hi>on</hi> to such a height of <hi>lust,</hi> that they think themselves not <hi>free</hi> from the commands of God, <hi>untill</hi> they can, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trouble of conscience, commonly commit whoredome with any body, and call their lust <hi>their God that is in them,</hi> as it is well known we have too many such a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> first sprung up from the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbyterian <hi>root;</hi> for before their time we had
<pb facs="tcp:114594:7"/> no such creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es: Therefore feare you <hi>the true God,</hi> and keep his Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he may deliver you from this <hi>fleshly lust that warres against the soule</hi> (for that lust i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n enemy) lest at last it bring you both soule and body to hell fire, here and hereafter for ever.</p>
            <p>For I count the <hi>Pox</hi> a spark of hell fire, and a type of the endless<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> torments of he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l; for some are torm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nted w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h it as long as they live, notwithstanding they <hi>repent</hi> and goe to <hi>Heaven</hi> when they die; but God gives over the other high Presbyters to their <hi>owne lust,</hi> and will not send the <hi>Pox</hi> among them, lest th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y should repent; <hi>why?</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cause he will pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gue and torment them hereafter for ever in <hi>hell;</hi> therefore you may be sure there is a <hi>hell</hi> to torment such a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shall commit spirituall whoredome; for God sent the <hi>Pope</hi> but of late dayes to be an <hi>emblem</hi> of Hel, out of which there is no Redemption. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10.</p>
            <p>And since I have entred upon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I shall <hi>parallel,</hi> and that according to the <hi>Scripture</hi> shew, that as whoredome is commonly accompanied with drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, swearing, wounding and killing one another about their whores, so is spirituall whoredome also; they are drunk, <hi>Isa.</hi> 29.9. they kill and wound soules, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.34.
<pb facs="tcp:114594:8"/> they sweare, <hi>Hos.</hi> 5.2, 3, 4. <hi>Psal,</hi> 139.19, 20. and they are drunk continually with their humours, there is never a sober word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Religion comes from them, that as drunkards, when they are drunk, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny speak <hi>at one time</hi> to one matter, and all is <hi>non sense;</hi> and then fall out, kill, and swe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, and wound one another about their whores: so these, in like manner, when they meet together, being drunk, with their jangling, half a score speak <hi>at one time</hi> to one matter, and all they speak is but <hi>non-sense;</hi> then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y fall out, excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and sweare one against another, wound and damn one anothers soul about their spirituall whores or Congregations: This is well known to be true: If you think I am immodest in my speech, look into <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and you finde the like, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.25, 26. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 32.19, 20. And the <hi>Council of State,</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> and all others, whosoever they be, consider also how <hi>unmovable</hi> they have found <hi>the faithfull and true Protestant to be in the time of triall,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8. but once a Presbyter, and then turne with any wind to any thing. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. And I pray God that the Army and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of State will be assi tant to the Lord Protector to bring in <hi>King Charles,</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:114594:8"/> therein consisteth the happinesse of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and of all the World; and let the Kings party and all others pray that it might be so, and not be <hi>wedded</hi> any more to their sins and vanities.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jewes</hi> expect their <hi>Messiah</hi> every <hi>Sabbath;</hi> but, say they, <hi>he is tied</hi> by the hair of a woman, <hi>and is so conscientious of that day,</hi> that he will not on it break the haire and come his way; <hi>but I rather thinke</hi> that the Devill sent some <hi>Lady,</hi> who by her tempting inchantments strives to keep him from his people, for the Devill knowes that when <hi>Messia</hi> cometh, there will be no place for them to abide in his kingdome.</p>
            <p>I heard a story once of a young godly <hi>gentleman</hi> who went to travell, came to <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and being <hi>at Court,</hi> he tooke his pleasure very much, that he <hi>forget</hi> what he was to doe, <hi>whereupon,</hi> a learned friend came unto him, <hi>saying,</hi> Sir, you must not give your selfe to such vaine, sinfull pleasures, you must bethink your self what you have to doe, <hi>else</hi> your Father will disinherit you; the young Genntleman answered him, saying, I will not lose my pleasure in <hi>Paris</hi> for my part in <hi>Paradise:</hi> It was a sad answer: I could wish that it were not the thoughts of any in our dayes.</p>
            <p>And therefore, I beseech you, <hi>pray</hi> for a
<pb facs="tcp:114594:9"/> right understanding that you may see and believe <hi>the truth that is opened unto you in this booke,</hi> and lay it to <hi>heart,</hi> and returne <hi>to God,</hi> with all your heart <hi>saying,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Father and Lord God <hi>Almighty,</hi> who is the only fountaine of light, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and understanding, guide me in the Reading of this booke with the holy spirit, and grant me the knowledge of the truth, and that I be setled in it, and live accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to it, to the glory of thy name, and the Comfortable peace of my soule. And grant the same spirit of grace to every one that Readeth this booke, that we all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thine onely spirit of truth, may be led thereby and knit together in love, through Jesus Christ thine only and holiest Sonne, and our blessed Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Black-friers,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 30, 1653. But according to the mis-apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the Vulgar. 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:114594:9"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought to shew these wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings before they were printed to his Highness the Lord <hi>Protector,</hi> but I finde he is <hi>kept</hi> (as the late <hi>King</hi> was) <hi>close Prisoner</hi> by flatterers, that his friends <hi>cannot</hi> come to speak with him, <hi>Jer. 22.15, 16.</hi> for the late <hi>King</hi> saith by experience <hi>(in his Speech to his Son)</hi> that Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are as unseparable from prosperous <hi>Princes,</hi> as Flies are from Fruit in <hi>Somer,</hi> whom adversity, like cold weather, drives away; and we finde in Scripture, that the same people, who after they were filled with the bread of Christ, acknowledged him greatly, would make him a King, and cried <hi>HOSANNA</hi> about him, <hi>John 6.
<pb facs="tcp:114594:10"/> 14, 15.26. Mat. 21.8, 9.</hi> when he was delivered to <hi>Pilate;</hi> and when <hi>Pilate</hi> gave them their choise whom they would have, <hi>Jesus</hi> or <hi>Barabbas,</hi> they desired a murtherer, and cried against the Prince of <hi>life,</hi> saying, <hi>Crucifie him, Crucifie him,</hi> Mark <hi>15.6, 7, 8, 9, 10,</hi> &amp;c. I believe, these things, being rightly considered, are very <hi>applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to these times, concerning some People and Souldiers affection in their <hi>Choise,</hi> if they could have but their <hi>choise;</hi> and blessed be God that doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it otherwayes, for his Elect sake, else we should be in a miserable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; But since by Gods providence I cannot come to his Highnesse, I hope that I say nothing in this ensuing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration concerning him, but what is <hi>truth,</hi> and therefore being confident in God, who directeth me in the way of truth, I, in Gods name, do send forth this truth as followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114594:10"/>
            <head>A moderate Vindication of his Highness the <hi>LORD PROTECTOR,</hi> From the popular Aspersion now cast upon Him.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare Friends, though I was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved not to write any more; yet because of Reproaches laid upon a Person of <hi>renown,</hi> which cannot easily be taken <hi>off</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>divine</hi> assistance from the <hi>Lord Almighty;</hi> I having <hi>Visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>Revelations</hi> sufficient, to shew his <hi>innocency;</hi> it being given for that <hi>purpose,</hi> think my selfe bound in <hi>Conscience</hi> to declare it, whatsoever the Result thereof <hi>may be,</hi> and therefore being necessitated thereunto, and seeing that much good may come to this <hi>Nation,</hi> to whom I ow, under God, all the respect that I can shew to them; <hi>I thought good</hi> to come forth in print againe, <hi>chiefly</hi> upon the abovesaid <hi>occasion,</hi> foreseeing that it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>speed,</hi> both for the <hi>Vindication</hi> of the Person and the <hi>Salvation</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> &amp; as a <hi>Mantle</hi> is as broad on the wrong side, as it is on the right side, so a false <hi>report</hi> sometimes is received, and goeth as far as the <hi>truth,</hi> specially when peoples judgments are partial,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114594:11"/> that through envy against some party they are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be deluded by <hi>lier,</hi> notwithstanding the clearenesse of the manifest <hi>truth</hi> shewing to the contrary against it so evident, that they cannot give reason <hi>why</hi> they believe such things, <hi>but stubbornly say it is so,</hi> and there is an end of it.</p>
            <p>Truly friends, I doe not speak these things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out experience, for I have tried it this two yeares or more, constantly arguing with many concerning his Highnesse the Lord Protector, against whom the malicious Presbyterians being th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ust out and fallen, <hi>through Gods just judgement upon them,</hi> like a mad <hi>Dog</hi> that runnes after the stone, but heeds not the hand that throwes it; so these impenitent ones, that stript his late M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jesty of his <hi>Militia</hi> and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and of all his Power, and turned him into the open <hi>Field;</hi> also sending by their commands, Troops and Companies after <hi>Him,</hi> with Swords in their hands to pursue and destroy him, who as surely kill'd him by their Commands, as <hi>David kill'd Uriab,</hi> 2. Sam. 12.9.13. <hi>but they will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke David,</hi> would now be quitted from his <hi>bloud,</hi> and lay it upon his Highnesse the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector.</p>
            <p>And for that end, did repo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t false things, and wrote private bookes against <hi>him,</hi> and by revi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ish instigation have bewitched the mindes of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallity of <hi>men,</hi> that it is believed and asserted with a great deale of false confidence, that they would have it to be an undeniable <hi>truth,</hi> for which they durst pawn their soules, and die for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof; yet the chiefest Authors are Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters of those <hi>Bookes,</hi> and Reports durst never appear to maintaine it; and therefore I do admire that men of quality, being sober men, Divines, Lawyers, Physitians, and I speak unto all sorts of men, I doe admire that you will take a Report of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114594:11"/> this matter and concernment, for a truth, which indeed may be the ruine of a Nation, when you h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve no grounds for it, but Rumour raised by some malicious discontented party, or a Pamphlet without a name to it.</p>
            <p>For my part I am of opinion, that we ought to judge <hi>charit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bly</hi> of things that are <hi>secret;</hi> and we have the Scripture for our rule in doing it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.15, 16, 17. for, saith the Scripture, <hi>he found her in the field and the hetrothed Damosell cried, and there was none to save her.</hi> Thus you see Gods word teacheth us to judge <hi>charitably;</hi> for saith he, <hi>The Damosell cryed,</hi> yet none knowes but she consented in the act, and is as guilty as the man; but because it cannot be proved against her, she must be justified as if she had <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed</hi> for help, and her repute and life must be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ese ved upon that account.</p>
            <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w it is evid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, by his actions, that the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> is not a bloud thirsty man; for it known <hi>how</hi> the Presbyterians sought <hi>his life,</hi> when they were in power; <hi>and after that,</hi> the levelling party sough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>his life; and thou</hi> the Independan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists sought <hi>his lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> all which pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties, through G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ds providence, fell into his hands; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse be had intellig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce, and knew them that were most against <hi>him,</hi> in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hese P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rties, yet which of them did he cause to be put to death, or trouble at all for his cause, by way of revenge? Truly had he fallen into their hands, they had made short work with him before this time; therefore why should any man think that the L. Protector had such a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to have the late Kings bloud, who never did him <hi>hurt,</hi> and let those go free <hi>that were his deadly enemies,</hi> when he had more power to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, than he had in the Kings dayes? Surely it can be no part of a reasonable mans Creed.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114594:12"/>
            <p>For, had he at the Kings death, <hi>been the Chiefe Generall,</hi> then one might have spoken something against Him for consenting to his death, because the <hi>Generall</hi> had a power to save the <hi>King,</hi> by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the <hi>Army</hi> to do it, and if a party of the <hi>Army</hi> had withstood him in it, a Declaration of foure lines had on a sodaine raised twenty thousand <hi>Londoners</hi> to assist him in it; but you will say, he durst not do it because of the <hi>Paliament;</hi> therefore I say, on the <hi>Parliament</hi> lieth <hi>the Kings hloud,</hi> and <hi>chiefly</hi> on them that sent out the first forces against <hi>him:</hi> If this be not true reason, which doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently prove who is <hi>guilty,</hi> and if I have not laid the <hi>burthen</hi> of the <hi>Kings bloud</hi> at the right <hi>doore,</hi> then speake you, and stand to it <hi>as openly as I doe,</hi> otherwayes lay your hand upon your mouth.</p>
            <p>Also it is evident by his <hi>Carriage</hi> in the field, that he was alwayes more inclinable to save, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy, if possibly it could be done with safety to himselfe and his <hi>Armie,</hi> and the most forward to have all the <hi>Articles of warre</hi> performed to his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but some other great one, much desired of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>if reports be true</hi> slew a valiant man, after he gave him quarter, &amp; disarm'd him, such doing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God will revenge, for it is no lesse then wilfull murther.</p>
            <p>And truly I may say something most Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble of the Lord Protector experimentally, <hi>and that is,</hi> If he had not beene more <hi>Cleare</hi> from the <hi>King,</hi> blood <hi>than</hi> any of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> I had not found <hi>him</hi> to be my freind, though unlook'd for, <hi>when all them were in a rage against me,</hi> and thought immediately to destroy me <hi>at the comming out of my first booke,</hi> for had he not beene <hi>innocent</hi> concerning the <hi>King,</hi> I in the <hi>said booke</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>claring so much for the <hi>King. Reason tells</hi> that he had beene the first m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainst <hi>me,</hi> but he was under <hi>God</hi> my <hi>Protector,</hi> and defended me against <hi>them;</hi> a strong argument
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114594:12"/> that he is <hi>innocent</hi> from the blood of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> before <hi>God,</hi> whatsoever men thinke of him.</p>
            <p>And I believe ingeniously, that his Highnesse by the providence of God will be the <hi>Chief</hi> instrument to establish both <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>King</hi> again in this land, for when he hath tried <hi>all,</hi> he shall find that to be his best course, and I am confident he lookes upon his honour at this time to be but a burthen to <hi>him,</hi> for the just mans <hi>innocencie</hi> is his greatest <hi>guard,</hi> neither is the covetous nor ambitious <hi>fit for honour or riches.</hi> However, it pleaseth God to bestow upon such that are <hi>Just and humble,</hi> both Honour and riches that are durable to posterity unto all <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> yet notwithstanding truly there is no greater <hi>signe</hi> of a <hi>princes</hi> fall, than when he is become <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible</hi> in the eyes of the <hi>people;</hi> we have had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience sufficiently for the <hi>truth</hi> of that in the late <hi>King</hi> &amp; the <hi>Parl.</hi> besides what the <hi>scripture</hi> sheweth. <hi>Job</hi> 12.21. <hi>Psal.</hi> 107.40 41. <hi>Isa</hi> 40.23. for, saith he, <hi>God poureth contempt on them,</hi> and indeed such things <hi>are meerly of God,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.15, 16. and it is time for a Prince to look about <hi>him</hi> when the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to slight <hi>him,</hi> and affront him, and not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>flatterers,</hi> who will say all is well, <hi>when</hi> there is no hope of what they say to be <hi>true;</hi> therefore let me tell you, it is not wisdom nor safety for the Lord Protector to stablish himselfe in the first Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, for God is against it, and all men are against it, except a few Flatterers; for there is an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour that must not be destroyed, nor disappoint d, <hi>Isa.</hi> 65.8, 9. But in the second Magnitude he shall be <hi>glorious</hi> before God and all the World; for then shall it be seen that he is not so <hi>self-ended,</hi> as now they think he is, and it will be a greater honour for <hi>him</hi> to set up the right <hi>King,</hi> to satisfie all, than for to be a King himselfe in daily <hi>care,</hi> and farre better for his Posterity and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> for then
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114594:13"/> there will be an end of the Warre and Taxes, and assurance of what he hath to Him and his Poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for ever.</p>
            <p>Oh what a sweet Harmony it is, when the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> blesse one the other, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Israel</hi> did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.18. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 1.47. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.20. then there is hope of <hi>glory</hi> and further happinesse to such a <hi>nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I remember a passage which an <hi>antient</hi> woman told me, being her observation of the various be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour of Queen <hi>Elizabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> and King <hi>James,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the People; Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> when she went ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oad, the people came from all about to see her, and she said to them all the way, the Lord blesse you, my good Subjects; <hi>and they answered her again, saying, the Lord blesse your Majesty,</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> she was greatly beloved for this very cause, and being <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> withall, she feared no <hi>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hery:</hi> But King <hi>James,</hi> when he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt abroad, and the people sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked about to see <hi>him,</hi> he fell to swearing at them, and saying, Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, are the people mad? Did they nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r see a <hi>man</hi> before? So the people returned discontented, and did not care for seeing Him: And this good custome of Q <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zabeth,</hi> which knit the he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts to her, was left off, through the perversnesse of King <hi>James,</hi> who could not abide the sight of a multitude, for feare of <hi>Treason,</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that the people knew not the sweetness of King <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e and Love to them, untill he dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed it up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Scaffold. Thus King <hi>James</hi> wilfully, and though a wise man, yet foolishly, brou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht a contempt upon himselfe and family hithe to.</p>
            <p>The reason why the people speak contemptible of the Lord P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>otector, is, fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st <hi>because of the scandall c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nc rning the late Kings Bloud.</hi> Secondly, <hi>because, he hath taken such honour upon him.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>because
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114594:13"/> they think he intends to aspire higher yet, and to continue the Taxes for to maintaine an everlasting Warre against the Family of CHARLES STUART,</hi> whom now they have in repute againe, seeing no hopes for them elsewhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; and it is a wonderfull thing to consider, how the very g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eatest enemies of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> I mean the Indep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nts and Anabaptists that met in <hi>Black fria s</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about a yeare or two agone, were mad against the Lord Protector, because he was not <hi>cruell enough</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainst the King and his Party, and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>efo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e would have him taken away, and set up <hi>Harrison</hi> in his place, now are they chang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and condemn th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Protector for his cruelty to the King and his pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty: I believe his Highnesse is not ignorant of all this, nor of the way to come off with credit and renown.</p>
            <p>There was a thing moved to me, by one that is of neare relation to his Highnesse; I wish it were come to effect; It is true, I made some progresse therein, and found much civility of the Protectors side; though I was unworthy of the honour to move a matter of that concernment to Ladies of such great account; and doubtlesse God will turn that respect they had to me for his <hi>name</hi>'s <hi>sake,</hi> to their high honour, and for the vaunting of others which have sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghted such motions; if things should fall ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as they would have it, <hi>I know they w ll fa e worser than now they doo,</hi> and that such a composure is best for them; for if by a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igne match &amp; power <hi>the King</hi> come in they shall be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pointed of their expectation, and being low now, they shall then be lower, and in greater slavery, for they that bring him in will have the Prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence: But if that things should be composed, and the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Duke matcb at home,</hi> then <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> might be <hi>settled,</hi> that at least every man should have his <hi>owne,</hi> and those that suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red for the <hi>Kings
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114594:14"/> cause</hi> should be preferred, or have some restitution in regard of their <hi>losses;</hi> for my own part I might be <hi>silent,</hi> for I am the least concerned in such busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, onely I think my selfe <hi>bound</hi> to shew men the <hi>truth,</hi> and what will be the issue of the <hi>one</hi> and of the <hi>other;</hi> and I know the <hi>prudent</hi> Royalist is of my minde.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now I shall (God willing) relate what Visions I had, to shew the innocency of the Lord Protector, and how he by Gods providence, will be the chief instrument to restore the King againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="vision">
               <head>The first Vision.</head>
               <p>I Fell into a <hi>Trance,</hi> and I was <hi>carried</hi> in the <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> into <hi>Whitchall</hi> to the <hi>Councill chamber,</hi> and being there alone the <hi>Protector</hi> came in hastily without any <hi>attendance,</hi> and I asked him what was the matter that he came alone, and where his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell was, <hi>and he answered me very kindely, but mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, that they had forsook him;</hi> and he went through the Room to a <hi>private doore,</hi> and lifting up the <hi>hanging</hi> goes away; thought I, I will not follow him, but I will see who will come hither: <hi>and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a little time</hi> there comes in <hi>a Man,</hi> who told me that the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> was in great danger, sought for by the <hi>Councill,</hi> but said he was got into a place whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they nor any of his foes could come at him; and I was glad he was got out of their hands; and the Man went away: After that comes a man from the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> to me, saying, <hi>his Highness</hi> desired me to send him a <hi>Handkerchief,</hi> whereupon I put my hand into my pocket and drew out a fair large Holland one, and sent it him, and after a long while the same <hi>messenger</hi> comes againe to me with the <hi>Handkerchief</hi> in his hand, <hi>so wet,</hi> as if it had been
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114594:14"/> dipt in a paile of <hi>water,</hi> and said that the <hi>Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> had <hi>wept</hi> all that <hi>since</hi> I sent him the <hi>Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief;</hi> and the <hi>messenger</hi> went away: then said I to my self, surely his Highness now repents for that he had a hand with them in the late Kings death: and as I was thus thinking, upon the <hi>table</hi> there appeared a <hi>Book,</hi> whereupon I went to the <hi>table</hi> and took up the <hi>Book,</hi> and as I read in it, I found it to be a <hi>Record</hi> of all <hi>Cromwell</hi>'s <hi>actions,</hi> and being desirous to read it in order, <hi>I turned to the first page,</hi> with an intent to read all, but upon the first leaf was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the very things that were done that present, namely, how he was with me in the <hi>Councill-chamber,</hi> and how he was pursued by his former <hi>Friends,</hi> and how I had sent him the <hi>Hankerchief,</hi> and how he had <hi>wept</hi> it wet with his <hi>teares,</hi> and that his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> and <hi>weeping</hi> wept all the <hi>actions</hi> that was against him out of the <hi>Book:</hi> And as I was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the goodnesse <hi>of God</hi> unto him, for I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood it was a <hi>Vision,</hi> and that the <hi>Record</hi> was Gods own writing, I awaked.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This signifies to me, and to all others that are not wllfully blinde, that he is cleare, what by Innocency, and what by Repentance, that I dare not say the contrary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="vision">
               <head>The second Vision.</head>
               <p>I Fell into a <hi>Trance,</hi> and immediately I was at <hi>White-hall</hi> at the <hi>Guard-chamber:</hi> And as I looked about me, <hi>I beheld</hi> the <hi>Late King,</hi> and the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> walking arm in arm together, and talking very friendly about some serious businesse, <hi>as I thought;</hi> and I heard the sound of their words, but could not understand the matter they talked of; and though I had a great desire to over-hear <hi>them,</hi> yet I durst not go no nearer to <hi>them,</hi> lest I should
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114594:15"/> give <hi>offence;</hi> and I knew that the King was <hi>dead,</hi> therefore I wondered that the Lord Protector was so great with him, <hi>saying to my selfe,</hi> This surely signifies, that the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> is not so guilty of the Kings Bloud as men think him to <hi>be;</hi> And as I was musing, there came a <hi>voice</hi> from <hi>above,</hi> say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s <hi>House is a sure House;</hi> and being troubled at it, I <hi>awaked;</hi> and as I was thinking in my Meditation at that crosse <hi>Vision,</hi> and saying to my selfe, Have I been deceived all this while. in declaring <hi>for Charles Stuart, Son to the Late King,</hi> and shall <hi>Cromwell</hi> now be his <hi>Heire?</hi> I fell into a <hi>Trance</hi> the second time, and was in the <hi>Guard-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> where the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued walking as before: Then came the <hi>voice</hi> againe, saying, <hi>Cromwells house is a sure house, for he shall bring in the Kings Son,</hi> whereupon I awaked with exceeding Joy, saying, Lord let his house stand for ever, on condition he set up the <hi>Kings Son,</hi> that we may have <hi>the true worship of God againe in the Church.</hi> And I fell the third time, and also the fourth time, into the same <hi>trance,</hi> having, as before, a little respite <hi>between,</hi> and seeing the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Protector</hi> together; and the <hi>Voice</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, saying, <hi>Cromwells house is a sure house, for he shall bring in the Kings Son,</hi> untill I was fully satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and confirmed of the truth thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>These Visions I had the last Somer upon two Lords dayes, and indeed they are so plaine as</hi> Josephs <hi>Visions were,</hi> Mat. 1.20, 21. Mat. 2.13.19, 20. <hi>that they need no interpretation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="vision">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114594:15"/>
               <head>The third Vision.</head>
               <p>I Fell into a <hi>Trance,</hi> and immediately I was in a place where <hi>a man</hi> was preaching, and giving some hints against the <hi>Lord Protector,</hi> but I being not aware of it, his Highnesse was there, and stood up, saying to the <hi>Minister,</hi> I am not such a <hi>Man</hi> as you take me to be, <hi>for I appeale to God:</hi> And as he spake these words, <hi>his cloaths fell open of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves miraculously, that his naked breast was seene, which was most cleare, having not on it neither spot nor blemish:</hi> Lord, said I, <hi>this</hi> is a wonderfull sign of his innocency; but it was a more wonderful thing to me to see him not <hi>burning himselfe againe;</hi> for, said I, he hath many enemies here, that perhaps have Pistolls to shoot at his <hi>naked breast;</hi> yet said I, <hi>God</hi> is with him, who hath all mens breath in his <hi>hands,</hi> that they cannot move a finger against <hi>him,</hi> and the <hi>Protector</hi> knoweth it; therefore he is as bold as a <hi>Lion,</hi> for his trust is in the <hi>LORD JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVAH;</hi> so with these thoughts I awaked, praising <hi>God</hi> for this <hi>Vision</hi> also.</p>
               <p>This Vision I had while <hi>I</hi> was about this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to confirm me further concerning the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of his Highnesse; and truly I saw this Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion partly fulfilled, for last <hi>Trinity Sunday</hi> in the morning, there was a Man preaching in the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, who spake home to his Highnesse: But as a Touch-stone is for the praise of pure Gold, so the word of Reproof and Triall meeting with the Heart of an innocent Man, causeth his Face to shine, that his inward part may be seen by a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scerning Eye, to be as cleare as the Glasse; I say so, because that of all Bodies, Glasse is most di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scernable, for a man may see quite thorough it.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114594:16"/>
               <p>One thing more is remarkable, Last Somer I was invited to dinner to a Gentlemans Chamber, and being come, there was a Knight and Baronet sate at dinner, who had a desire to have some dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with me; He was a great lover of the King, and as far as I could finde him, being but a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to him, he was a vertuous, ingenious, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man; and after some time spent in discourse with them about what I had written, and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my hope of the Lord Protectors integrity, I came away.</p>
               <p>But the same night the Knight had a Dream or Vision, thus,</p>
               <p>He thought that there was an Order come forth, That all the Gentry of <hi>England</hi> should come up to <hi>London</hi> for to make the <hi>Lord Cromwell</hi> KING; And he thought they all came to <hi>London,</hi> and met in a great Hall, and every man sate in his place according to his degree, he being also in his place among them, and that the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and the <hi>Crown</hi> was set upon his <hi>head,</hi> and when this was done, the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the end of the Hall, and opened the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings to goe to another Room, from whence he comes back againe with the King in his right hand into the middle of the Hall, and takes the Crowne from off His Head, and layes it at the Kings Feet; then was the King Crowned, and much Rejoicing at it: And the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> also was mightily exalted by the King, Nobles, and People, and highly commended for his faithfulness. Thus ended the Vision.</p>
               <p>And when I went afterwards to see the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at his Lodging, that had invited me, he told me how the Knight had a Dream that night which convinced them to be of my opinion concerning the Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and related the same unto me as it is above written.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114594:16"/>
               <p>Other Visions I had concerning his Highnesse, to the same purpose; and severall others have seen Visions and told them unto me, which <hi>I</hi> omit to declare for brevitie sake; therefore I beseech you not to judge rashly concerning his Highness, lest you erre therein and offend God: But, as I said before, Judge charitably, for in so doing you cannot erre, and thereby you shall obey God. <hi>Deuteronomie</hi> 22.15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now let me tell you what I have observed, and learned concer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing the late Kings being in the Army, and so forward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the King was brought to the Army, he was very well pleased with his Condition, being kindely courted with the chiefest Commanders, and the Protector: <hi>Fairfax,</hi> besides other Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were very great with him, and had their design upon some good and honourable tearmes for both sides to restore him againe.</p>
               <p>But others of the Army suspecting such things, and seeing the Lord Protector, <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and others, so great with the KING, and themselves, who thought their Interest in the Army was as great as <hi>theirs;</hi> the King not taking such notice of them, they were filled with envy and rage against the King and the party he favoured more than they; therefore they stirred up the Army against their chief Commanders, saying, that now such and such men did desert the Cause; and for their owne ends and preferment, intended to let all their labour be lost, and set up the King againe as before; then the temper of the Army was such, that they were more apt to catch at the shadow, than to hold the substance (for they looked for some great matters to come in the end, yet found nothing but deceit) that all the Army soon listned to those men, and began to consult what course to take in this case,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114594:17"/> for to break the design concerning the Kings Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation.</p>
               <p>And the same envious men made also a strong party in the Parliament House to be of their side, which Parliamenteers under pretence of zeal and holinesse, strove for no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hing but greatnesse. And now finding an oportunity (in hope to obtaine their owne ends by it) were not negligent to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the <hi>Kings</hi> designe, and close with the humor of these men of the Armie, so they drive on the same businesse as fierce in the House, as the other did in the Armie.</p>
               <p>Whereupon, the Armie was so offended against the <hi>Protector, Fairfax,</hi> and others because of their dealing with the King, that they would no longer trust them, but they must have their agitators to stand for them against their Commanders, and therefore they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>use out two of them that were the most fiercest against the King, in eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y company throughout the armie, and what they doe now must be the law, and these agitators being set on by the adv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rse party, grew so high, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders could not doe nothing but what they pleas'd.</p>
               <p>Then the King seeing thi mischief against him, and finding the Lord Protector was the most pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent faithfull man among them, and fittest to be imployed, because the Armie generally then had a respect unto him; I say the King being guided with the spirit of <hi>David.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.32.34. sends <hi>Gromwell</hi> amongst the agitators, as <hi>David</hi> sent <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shai,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he might send him word of what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to doe, and the <hi>Lord Cromwell</hi> finding that they intended with a strong party to breake th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough the guard, and to murther the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Hampton Court,</hi> whereupon he doubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd and fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gives the <hi>King</hi> notice of it, who removes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114594:17"/> immediately upon that to the Isle of <hi>Wight,</hi> and disappoints the Agitators that thought violently to break all their purposes by murthering the <hi>King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the <hi>King</hi> seeing nothing but death before his eyes, now commits himself to God, and referrs his cause to the managing of his Highnesse the Lord <hi>Protector.</hi> His Highnesse finding the adverse party had made themselves so strong, both in the House and Army, that there was no way for him to break them, but closely to go along with them; and that the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly way for him to keep himselfe in power, was, to be the most forward in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe, hoping in due time, God would by his wisdome turn the tide; and judging it but a folly for him to <hi>strive against the Stream,</hi> or yet to desert the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my, for then he had been uncapable to doe any thing according to his promise, for the <hi>King,</hi> or his <hi>Seed</hi> after him.</p>
               <p>Now things were so strangely carried on, hudl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d among all parties, and every party feared the other, and knew not what to doe, but were at their wits ends; then the Presbyterians thought that if the Independant did set up the King, they should goe to ruine, and be called to account for the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oud of the Nation; and therefore their Consciences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guilty, to quit themselves, and for feare, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that if his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>jesty would take all the Bloud that was spile, upon himselfe, they would set him up; and the King (poore Soule) was forced to doe any thing whatsoever they demanded of him, provided it was not against his Oath, in hopes to have peace for Himself and Subjects. Thus the Presbyterian sets the Trap, and makes the way Ready, and the other adverse party takes the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from it to bring the King to his end, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114594:18"/> his Highnesse could not oppose it, but to keep himselfe in, was forced to be the most forward in it, though against his will. Now the King being put to death, every one sought to advance him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, but his Highnesse waited what the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God would bring forth, he moving in his Sphere diligently.</p>
               <p>Then he was called to go for <hi>Ireland,</hi> to avenge the massacre that the Irish made upon the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants there, and their injury done to his late Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, by pretending they had a Commission from him to doe those vile acts, and God sufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers them into the hand of his Highnesse, which rewards them according to their works: After that he came over to <hi>England</hi> againe.</p>
               <p>The young King being also come to <hi>Scotland</hi> now, by Gods providence, though for no other end, but for to bring a just judgement upon the proud Presbyters, who notwithstanding, the King in Person was among them, did not value him; would do the Work themselves, and said to the King and Protestant party, <hi>Stand by thy selfe, come not neare me, for I am holier than thou,</hi> Isa. 56.5.</p>
               <p>They thinking to have the Honour to themselves, and that the King should wait upon them, and be beholding to them for his owne, insomuch that He should be no more than a Cypher, which of it selfe signifies nothing, but serves to make up the number, so that he should have beene a King in Name, and no King but at their Pleasure, for their own Ends, to countenance their further De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe upon <hi>England.</hi> And these Presbyters being gathered together, <hi>Fairfax,</hi> forsooth, would rather lay down his Commission (though he could hold'it while the King was put to death) than goe against his Brethren in iniquity: And now God by his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114594:18"/> providence exalts the Lord Protector to be the Lord Generall of the Armie, I say God did exalt him, for I am sure the Parliament would not have done it, if they could have chosen; so he goeth to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and God now remembring their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief against the Late King, and their slighting of his Sonne, which was then among them, delivers them at <hi>Dunbar</hi> into his hands, who rewarded them according to their works, and brought downe their proud Spirits ever since.</p>
               <p>After this, God remembring the Parliaments wickednesse against the Late King, by his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence makes his Highnesse to be the Avenger on them, and to thrust them out of doore like so many Fugitives and Vagabonds, that had murthered their King.</p>
               <p>And now to shew what the greatest enemies of all to God and Kingly Government, would be at, God puts in the heart of his Highnesse, the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector to call a company of Anabaptists and other Sectaries together, yet wisely compounds them with other solid Men, that were able to watch them and defeat them: And these Sectaries having the reigne, call themselves a Parliament, forsooth, and think to bring an absolute Confusion among us, and to destroy his Highnesse, and set up a bloody man of their owne chusing; but his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse being guided by such excellent wisdome as they are not capable of, having them, as it were, in a string, that when they had discovered themselves, and made themselves odious to all the world, and thought to perfect their designe by destroying Ministrie and Ministers, Law and Lawyers, and all others that would not immediately receive their confused wicked opinion; then his Highness takes them downe, which makes them ever since against
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114594:19"/> him. God be pleased, that alwayes gives <hi>Curst Cowes short horns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which Acts are the remarkable Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of God (especially this last) which the King could not have done for himselfe, for divers Reasons that may be given; yet by Gods providence his Highnesse did them; which things, being well considered, is the stablishing of Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the destroying of the Rebels for ever.</p>
               <p>Neither doe I think, that all these Acts were done by his Highnesse alone, but also by them that go along with him; and I dare say, and doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, that both hee and they, are endowed with such wisdome, and temperance, that they are, of all others in the world, the most fittest men to rule, and that his Majesty will be the most happiest Prince in the world by agreeing with them, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them his Counsel; and that it is the wisdom of all others, notwithstanding they be Peeres, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever else, to be content to enjoy their own again peaceably, and to leave the mannaging of Affaires to the King and these men, untill they are of a better temper, acknowledging their weaknesse in managing the Affaires of the Kingdomes in the Late Kings dayes, to his ruine, and their owne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so.</p>
               <p>Thus ye have a relation of what his Highnesse hath done in order for the stablishing of the King againe, and what now remaine h for him to doe, but to bring in the King and set him on the Throne, that his Highnesse may be also established as the most worthiest to be the second Family and to reigne with him for ever.</p>
               <p>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Argument more for to vindicate the Lord Protector, by comparison, which I hope you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114594:19"/> deny; I speak to you sober godly men that knew the late King, and were conversant with him, and doe testifie what a godly religious Prince he was, a true Protestant, a just and a mercifull Man, a wise and a prudent Man, the most humble and meeke King that ever <hi>England</hi> had, a man that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired really the good of his Subjects, and rejoyced to see them flou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ish in all blessings. This testimony of him I had from many of you whom I account to be Gods Jewels in this nation, <hi>Malachi.</hi> 3.16, 17. yet you know how the old Serpent by his skilfull ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing instruments, the Presbyterian f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction, got an advantage against the King, by their lies, and never left, him untill they had raised his subject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion against him, and at last slew him; But his death will be their death, <hi>Hosea</hi> 13.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54.55, 56, 57.</p>
               <p>You know how they said, that the King was a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and would have brought in an arbitrary Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Popery, how he was a bloody man, that did not care, though all his subjects throats were cut so he might obtaine the foresaid ends; moreover saying, he was a Swearer, a Drunkard, a Who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e master, a vile Person, that hated all good men, and that the Queene was a Whore and all her children Bastards; saying also, that the King was not endued with sense and reason, that he was led away like a child by evill counsell, and because of his wants in naturall parts, he was not fit to Reigne. Truly these reproaches cast upon the Royall family are so odious to me, that I can hardly set them downe, but I see it is needfull, and the examples of the Evangelists presse me on to doe it: and as they set downe the rep oaches of Christ, that it might be to his eternall glory, and to the ever
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114594:20"/> lasting shame of the Pharisees; so in like mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this will be for the glory of the Royall family for ever, and to the shame of the Presbyters, to all eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Which things raised against the Royall family, you know are all lyes, yea and all now know it was nothing but malicious lyes, raised without the least cause or any ground of suspition for it at all, yet these things were so asserted in Pulpits and in Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and believed for the time that many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands lost their lives to maintaine those lyes.</p>
               <p>Then since this skilfull Apollyon, enemy to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. could do this in time of Peace, by slandering the late King, and bring so many thousand men to dest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uction by it, how much more mischiefe will he doe now in time of Warre, against the Lord Protector, to keep the King and him off from making Peace againe? For I believe, that the Presbyterians, being afraid that yet they must give an account, are in despaire, and doe what mischief they can to keepe off the King and his Highnesse, from making an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment And though they seeme to be of both sides, some with the King, others with the Lord Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor; yet it is to set on foot what plots they can against the one, and against the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying poore innocent soules to act it; but they doe it subtilly with a bewitching infusion, and are not found in it; therefore I say to you that are reall of the Kings party, believe no evill report against the Lord Protector; and you that are reall of the Protectors party, believe no evill report against the King; for I tell you, Sathan is busie to set you on plots to your owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction; for be sure that King <hi>CHARLES</hi> gives no consent to any plot against his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114594:20"/> his person, neither doth his Highnesse consent to any plot against his Majesties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, what is done in the high Places of the Field, is another case: and take heed, that if such things should happen against either of the foresaid Persons, lest he that did it, and bring the newes, should have such a reward as <hi>David</hi> gave one that brought him newes of <hi>Saul</hi>'s death, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15, 16. and them that brought him <hi>Sauls</hi> Sonnes head. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>I know there is nothing will be more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to the Presbyters, and them of the Rotten Parliaments, than to see the Fall of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the Lord Protector, and to have him in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rision like themselves, though on the other side they beare no good will to the King; if it be his will, God grant them grace to repent and be better minded: I love their Persons, but I hate their qualities, hypocrisie, malice, and wilfull blindenesse; for they pretend to know the Scripture, which if they did, they might see their errors: I doe admire at their blindenesse and malice against Bishop <hi>Laud,</hi> which made them so mad as to lose their reason, whereas indeed they should have blessed God for sending them such a man.</p>
               <p>You know, that in the beginning of the Parliament, the Communion Table was ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted three steps above the rest of the Church, and the ends thereof were turned North and South, with a raile about it, that the whole Body of the Church might discerne the Lords Body upon the Communion Table, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11.29. and see the two Ministers in their white Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices break the Bread, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out the Wine,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114594:21"/> one at the one end of the Table, and the other at the other end thereof, like those two An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels all in white, one at the head, and the other at the feet, where the Body of the Lord Jesus lay. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> 20 12.</p>
               <p>And for the Railes about the Communion Table, is there not good Reason and Scripture for that? D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>Joseph</hi> of <hi>Aramathea</hi> bury the Body of Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ist in an open Field, where the Swine might digg up, and the Doggs eat his Flesh? Did he not bu y him in an inclosed Garden, <hi>John</hi> 19.41. where Doggs and Swine could not come? Moreover, Did he not lay him in a new Tombe, hewed out of a <hi>Ro k,</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e there was no Corruption, and then roule a great <hi>Stone</hi> upon the Doore of it, so that not so much as a Worme could come neare the Body of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sus? <hi>Mathew</hi> 27.57, 58, 59, 60. And are not these things written to the end that the like care might be had of that resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of his Body in the Sacrament, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is more than a resemblance to a faithfull soule that discernes the Lords Body there, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.26, 27, 28, 29. therefore what Bishop <hi>Laud</hi> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in these things, was decent, and so agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scripture, that it cannot be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
               <p>But these bruitish Presbyterian Parliaments, as men which are in all the rest of their actions v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd of reason, so they are also in this, They will levell the Chancell, they will downe with the Communion Table into a bottome, that none in the Church can see it, except they come to it, They wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l downe with the Railes, that the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ggs may come and eat at the Table as well as the Minister; indeed D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ggs are Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114594:21"/> good enough for such Ministers as their<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are: They will turne the Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e end-way, that none in the Church can hardly see the Bread and the Wine upon the Table, if it were higher, for the Ministers and the Clerks about it. Is this the way for men to discerne the Lords Body, or to see the invisible Creator in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible Creature, when the Creature is as invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to them as the Creator? Oh the folly of these wise Men of <hi>Gotham,</hi> that pretended themselves to be Saints, and to know the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and all things else, That they should be so void of Scripture<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Reason, as not to see their Errors: Methinks if they but looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Baiber-Chy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urgion's Signe, and conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, they might have seene their folly in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Communion Table end-way, by that; and also by setting it in a bottom, for the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Chyru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>geon mounts his Signe on high, that all might see side-way the Body on it; so also the Christian Signe of the Sacrament ought to be in the Church, where it might be most visible to all the People, and the Ministers all in white Garments, to hold forth the body of the Lord Christ according to the Scripture and Reason; but now by any visible signe a man shall not know whether there will be a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion such a day in the Church or no, untill they are upon it.</p>
               <p>Then for those shining Garments, called Copes, that our Ministers had in Cathedrall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, to weare on high dayes, as <hi>Easter,</hi> and the like, <hi>John</hi> 19.31. Do they not represent those Angels? <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4, 5. And why doe the Evangelists va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in relating the habit of these Angels? One saith they had shining Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ments, as if they
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114594:22"/> had been embrodered with Gold and Silver, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4. The other saith, they were in white, as if they had beene in pure Linnen Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>John</hi> 20.12. the reason is, because the Ministers of Christ should have respect to the dayes of Christ, namely, the Day of his Birth, the Day of his Resurrection, and the like, and demonstrate it by their change of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>And why doth S. <hi>Mark</hi> say, that there was but one cloathed in a long white Garment, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.5. but to shew us that one Minister in a Church will serve; and you know we had but one in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>very little Church throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to shew us what manner of Garment the Minister must have, that is, a long white Garment, downe to the feet, as you know the Surplice was such a one.</p>
               <p>Now these severall Garments, appointed for the Ministers of the Gospel, in which the first Ministers thereof, even the Angels, appeares, were typified in the Law by the <hi>Ephod;</hi> for there was a rich embrodered <hi>Ephod, Exod.</hi> 28.6. <hi>Exod.</hi> 39.2, 3. and that is according to St. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4. And there were also <hi>Linnen Ephods,</hi> Exod. 39.27: 1 Sam. 29.18. and that is according to St. <hi>John</hi> 20.12. Therefore I say, they are altogether blind which refuse the Reformation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in respect to such Garments; for you see what grounds we have, both in the Old and New Testament, for the Cope and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice; and sure they are not the Ministers of Christ, that will refuse them to weare: And if you will object and say, the Apostles had no such Garments, I answer, no more had <hi>Aaron,</hi> at first, any Ephod; but when God provided those
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114594:22"/> Garments for him, it was not lawfull for him or his Sonnes to cast them by, and come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord without them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.2.43. therefore I say, the <hi>Apostles</hi> practice, which was like <hi>Aarons</hi> practice when he came first out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> while things were unsetled, are no more Rules to the Ministers now, than <hi>Aarons</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice at his first coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> were to be followed in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, when all things were gloriously setled.</p>
               <p>And why doth <hi>Mathew</hi> also say there was but one, Angel and that he descended from Heaven, and that he was so strong, that he rowled the Stone away that kept Jesus under, and that he was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, his Countenance being like Lightning, that no Creature could stand before him, but such as sought Jesus for to worship him; yea, the armed Souldiers for feare of him did shake, <hi>and became as dead men.</hi> Math. 28.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. But to shew us what Almighty power the Minister hath, especially the Chief Bishop, that doth all things decently, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 14.40. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the written Word of God, as we had it in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and to shew for U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity sake there must be Order, and but one Chief Minister, whom the rest must obey, who is also to command every Minister to respect the other, according to his Degree above him.</p>
               <p>And why doe <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> call them Angels, <hi>Mathew</hi> 28.2.5. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.12. and <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> call them Men, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.4. but for the end that we should esteeme of the true <hi>Minister<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of God, as of the Angells of God, that worship him, and shew us how to worship him, bringing the glad tydings of Salvation?</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114594:23"/>
               <p>And for bowing at the Name of Jesus, when we worship him, is there not an expresse command for it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. <hi>that every knee should how?</hi> That is, the knee of the Body, as well as the knee of the Heart. And doth not <hi>David</hi> give us an example, and invite all to doe it? <hi>Psalm</hi> 95.6. Saying, <hi>O come let us worship, and bow downe, and kneele before▪ the Lord our Maker.</hi> Surely if it was lawfull to bow in the time of the Law, for in the Law lies all the grounds the Enemy hath against bowing, How much more lawfull is it to bow in the time of the Gospel, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bowing is not Forbidden, but Commanded? <hi>Rome</hi> 14.11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Eph</hi> 3.14.</p>
               <p>And how beautifull was the worship of God in the Quire, where God was <hi>wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sh pped in the beauty of holinesse,</hi> Psal. 29 2. Psal. 96.9. <hi>with Songs, and praised according to the injunction of David,</hi> Psal. 105. 1 Chron. 16.42. <hi>with Voices and all instruments of Musick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly I found, when I was but a Child, that it was the first moving cause that brought me to be well affected with coming to Chu ch, for there is nothing will take Children, and quiet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m at the Church, so much as Musique, and tempers them to listen to the Preacher; for afterward every Sunday we had a Sermon in the Quire; and this was a good way to bring children to the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch; but now there is no moving cause to draw them to Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, that they might be quiet and learne, for they cannot abide at fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st to come to a crowd, and stay an houre or two there to see a man talke above them, and no body must say nothing but he, this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to the natu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of a childe, and to beat them to it is to break their spirits, and spoile them; I
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:114594:23"/> speak it by experience; for, being in <hi>Black-friers</hi> at a Funerall Sermon, I observed it, That when the Minister went up to the Pulpit, and began to speak, a Childe being in his Mothers armes cried out against him, calling him <hi>Bolole,</hi> and could not by any meanes be perswaded but it was some evill thing, and immediately his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was forced to take him away, and thought the Childe was frighted and spoyled, neither could he abide to come to Church any more: but if the Organs had beene up, and the same Childe had been once to heare them, he would have beene as ready to goe to Church as any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>But now, except the Protestant Religion be established here againe, there is no hopes that the next Generation will be but Atheist; for Presbyter is the Mother of Confusion; and wheresoever it is established, there must be hot Persecution, and then followeth Confusion and Destruction, for their immoderate Teaching will cause their Hearers to depart from them, and flie in their faces.</p>
               <p>We read (<hi>Revelat.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11.) that from under the Altar the soules of them that were slaine for the Word of God, and for the Testimony they held, cried to God for to revenge their blood on their Adversaries, and they had a good answer to it; ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k, <hi>They died for the Word of God, and for the Testimony which they held.</hi> These were setled in their Faith, and had a Creed, and a Worship, which all of them agreed <hi>in,</hi> died <hi>for,</hi> and held forth <hi>to</hi> the World; and there is such a distinction made between their Testimony and the Word of God, as if all that were necessary for Faith, and for the worship of God, were drawne
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:114594:24"/> out of the Bible, and composed into another Book, here called a Testimony, and elsewhere the Booke of Life, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 20.12. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.1. but vulgarly called the Communion-Booke, or Booke of Common-Prayer, which Book is so di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguished from the Bible, and so exalted by the Bible, as if the life of all that is in the Bible, were in the Gospel-Book, for so we call it in Welch, which Book, without question, is the Testimony held forth, for which these righteous Soules were slaine. Now consider, you Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, how farre you are from having Communion in Faith with these Soules under the Altar, and especially you, that looke upon your selves to be the Saints, who follow <hi>Feak, Sympson,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers;</hi> suppose that a man should examine you one by one, concerning the Articles of your Faith, and begin with <hi>Feak</hi> and <hi>Sympson,</hi> I am sure a man should finde that you have as many Creedes as men, but never a true one, so that a Protestant may say unto you, as Christ said to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> John 4.22. <hi>you</hi> believe you know not what, <hi>we</hi> know what we believe, and <hi>you</hi> worship you know not how, nor you know not what you worship, but <hi>we</hi> know what we worship, and how we worship God, for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is among the Protestants; for the Papists also worship they know not what, Stocks and Stones, and in an unknowne Tongue, and they are as bad as you, that a learned Jew came among them, then to you, but he could not finde rest untill he came to the Protestant Church, and you may finde him every Sunday at St. <hi>Peters Paul</hi>'s-<hi>wharfe</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> if you please. Thus much for you Poore soules, who think your selves Rich. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17, 18.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:114594:24"/>
               <p>I am of that opinion, That <hi>Saul</hi> and his House were a sort of Puritans or Presbyterians, and that <hi>David</hi> and his house were of our Protestant Religion, and my reasons are these,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Saul,</hi> without any regard to the authority of the Priest, would assume to offer Sacrifice. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.9, 10 11, 12, 13, 14. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. so the Presbyters do assume to be Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, yet cannot prove that they have any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority descentive from hand to hand from the Apostles.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Saul</hi> had an Evill Spirit, that could not abide Musique, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.10, 11, 12. so the Presbyters cannot abide Musique in the worship of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Saul</hi>'s Daughter could not abide <hi>David</hi> because of his Musique and Dauncing to the glory of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.14.16.20. so you know the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters cannot abide Musique and Dauncing, though it be done to the glory of God, at <hi>Christmas, Easter,</hi> and <hi>Whitsontide,</hi> and at other Times.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Saul</hi> made no conscience of Oaths, but through his Zeale, forsooth, he despiseth the Wisdome of his Fore-fathers; therefore he breaks the Oath, and would slay the harmlesse Gibeonits, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. and all the Nation must smart for his foolish bloudy act; so the Presbyters Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were such Zelots, they despise the wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of our former Parliaments, break their Oaths of their Allegiance and Supremacy to the King, and the Oath to the Church and Bishop, and slay them.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Saul</hi> was as malicious a Man as any of those times, for you see how he hunted for the life of <hi>David</hi> without any cause. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.11. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:114594:25"/> 1.10. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. And did not the Presbyrers the like, and worse, to the King and his party?</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Saul,</hi> for <hi>David</hi>'s sake, slew, by his command, fourescore and five persons of the Lords Priests, that did weare a Linnen Ephod, saith the Text, and destroy all they had, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.17, 18, 19. And did not the Presbyters, for the Late King <hi>Charles</hi> his sake, run and destroy the Bishops, and all the Ministers that did weare the Surplice? Thus the Holy Spirit sets downe the Garments of those faithfull Priests (which argues that some Priests fell with <hi>Saul,</hi> and did not weare the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phod) to the end that we might understand, that <hi>Saul</hi> and some false Priests, at last, could not abide those holy Garments, no more than the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters can abide the Surplice.</p>
               <p>But <hi>David</hi> was a great Prophet, who might, as he was a type of Christ, offer Sacrifice, the Priest never reproves him for it; he delighted in Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sique, and ordeined it to be in the Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.31.32 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.42 He was very conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious of his Oaths, and mercifull to his Enemies, bore no Malice, <hi>Psalm.</hi> 15.4. <hi>Psalm</hi> 24 3, 4. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119 106. He loved those Priests that did weare the Ephod, and observed the Law and Rules of the Church, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.6.9, 10, 11, 12. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.20, 21, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>And are not the true Protestants of King <hi>Davids</hi> minde? Do not the Protestant Ministers prove their Ministrie to come to them from hand to hand, by descent from the Apostles? Doe they not delight in Musique and Dauncing? Doe they not love Ministers and Bishops that observe their Oaths, Orders, and holy decent Garments? Doe they not love the Church, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114594:25"/> to have Choristers and Musique there againe? Are they not more mercifull, charitable to the Poore, and to all, than hard-hearted Presbyters? And doe they not keep their Oaths, though it cost them all they have? Yea, many lose their lives for it.</p>
               <p>And is it not here evidently seene, that the Protestant is of King <hi>Davids</hi> Family, which must stand, and blessed is he that bluids it; <hi>Psalm.</hi> 12 2.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.12, 13. And the Presbyterian is of King <hi>Sauls</hi> Family, and must fall, like the Walls of <hi>Ierico,</hi> and cursed is he that builds it. <hi>Josh.</hi> 6.20.25. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 16.33, 34.</p>
               <p>Now the great Object, which causeth all the errors that are in the world, is this, All would wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God after the manner of the Apostles, and yet they cannot see, nor agree among themselves what manner of worship that was: And the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists would make men believe strange things, as if the Apostles were not honest, but had delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one thing by Writings, and the clean contrary by word of mouth: And so it was of old with <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roboam, Ahab,</hi> and others, that they sought for the Primitive Rule: <hi>Jereboam</hi> goes beyond the Law, to <hi>Bethell,</hi> because <hi>Jacob</hi> testified the House of God to be there, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.17.19.22. and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes the Church, according to his thoughts, right, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.28, 29, 30, 31, 32 33, but <hi>Ahab</hi> thought to goe farther, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16.30, 31, 32, 33. and <hi>Manasseth</hi> thought good to goe beyond him, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 11. All these thought to be better Reformers than <hi>David,</hi> but it proved the Ruine of all them that did forsake his Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which though it was but young then, yet it was in all things, according to the Word and Minde of God, and the patterne shewed in the Mount, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114594:26"/> 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.44, 45, 46, 47. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.5. that the Church was not compleat in the worship of God, untill he came; for he understood the holy Fathers, and <hi>Moses</hi> his minde, figu ed in his Writings, 1 <hi>Chronicl.</hi> 28.19. and exceededs them in wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.98, 99, 100. Now observe <hi>David,</hi> and you shall finde that he takes the Law for his Rule in all that he doth, and so you sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l finde likewise, that our Church was exactly refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, according to the written word in all things.</p>
               <p>But some men will say, If your manner of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship be the onely true worship of God, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had not the Apostles such Chu ches, with Cho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isters, and such like Worship as you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s is?</p>
               <p>I answer, Why had not <hi>Moses</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like Worships in all things, as <hi>Solomon</hi> had, when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the Temple, and set all things in order <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Davids</hi> minde? The reason is, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would not have such a glorious Worship, but because he could not have it so the people being but a few, and in a Wilde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nesse, and their power sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt in comparison of <hi>Solomons</hi> power, to doe i; nor was <hi>Israel</hi> then come to the <hi>Land of Promise,</hi> where this Worship was to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> accomplished, and compleat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d.</p>
               <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat is the ve y same cause, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles had not the like Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ship in all things, as we had in King <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les</hi> his tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</p>
               <p>First they wanted p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wer to set up such Chu ches and Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ship.</p>
               <p>Secondly they wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and money to doe it. And what keeps us Protestants from enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying that worship now, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the want of pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, men and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? else would we have it up againe, but God wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l shortly s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pply all y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, then shall we sing <hi>Allelujah</hi> againe, <hi>Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:114594:26"/>
               <p>And if you would needs goe to the Primitive time, you should observe what the Angels did at Christs Birth and Resurrection, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y were the first Ministe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And you see also, that in the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Testament hey have Songs and Musique in the worship of God. <hi>Revolat.</hi> 14.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p>And why doe not the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, Anabaptists, say <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds Prayer?</p>
               <p>First, they cannot ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l God <hi>Father,</hi> because he is not the Father of such mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hers.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they cannot abide that any thing should be <hi>Hallowed,</hi> no no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> so much as the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of God, though we read in the New Testamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of a Holy P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, <hi>Math.</hi> 21.15. which ought not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and despised, by being disorderly in it, 1 <hi>Corin.</hi> 11.18.22. and of a Ho y M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t also, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. yea, and that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve power by the word of God to make holy eve y morsell of meat that we eat, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3.4.5.</p>
               <p>Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dly, they cannot abide Order, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r if Gods Will were <hi>done on Earth, as it is in Heaven,</hi> where all keep their orders, there would be no place found for them, who are nothing but confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they think it needlesse to say, <hi>Give us ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Daily B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead,</hi> for they wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e all from men by violence.</p>
               <p>S x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, they cannot forgive my sinne tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is done against them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> therefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y should s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give us, as we fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>give,</hi> they should nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r have their sinnes fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>given them.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, for <hi>Evil,</hi> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the paths thereof, and would not be <hi>delivered</hi> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir evill way.</p>
               <p>Eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly, they cannot say to God, <hi>Thine is the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngdome, the Power and the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ory,</hi> for they would
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114594:27"/> have the Kingdome, Power and Glory, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and for these Reasons they say not the Lords Prayer, nor they cannot abide those Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters that say it.</p>
               <p>The people of God alwaies glorified God, by leaving behind them a Record of his goodnesse to them: If you observe the Records concerning King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. and <hi>Edward</hi> the 6: you shall find that in those times they entred into certaine Oaths, for to extirpate Pope you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Land; and it pleased God to endue them with power to performe their Oaths, that they did it with ease, and setled also the True Religion; b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t observe their O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ths, and you shall finde them run and conclude in these words, I. A. B. doe vow thus, <hi>Help me O God with all thy Saints:</hi> he e they pray one for ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her, that God would help <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem to performe their Oaths. Now these O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hs were set downe to the end that future Parliaments shou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d obeserve their Rules in such a matter: But alas, our latter Parliaments scorn'd their Rules: and they make so many Oaths, the one to contradict the other, that they were not able to performe any of them, and brought a cu se and confusion, not onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themselves, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> also upon the whole Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they observed not the Rules of those good men.</p>
               <p>Therefore I say, let no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n deceive himselfe, nor think that any who hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ken all the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ths and Covenants, made since the beginning of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se late Parliaments, shall ever come to be the most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he Tabernacle of God, or be chief upon his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly Hill; for <hi>David</hi> sheweth plainely who shall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Father of the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, or who shall stand in the place of Jesus Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st <hi>Ps<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l.</hi> 15.4, tells us it is he that sweare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114594:27"/> his owne hurt and changeth not, shall be the Man; &amp; I am sure that is K. <hi>Charls,</hi> who hath also perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all that is requieed in that 15. <hi>Psalm,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found faithfull to the Death, hath obtained the Crowne of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.12. and <hi>Psal.</hi> 24.3, 4, 5. the question is put forth thus, <hi>Who shall ascend into the Hill of the Lord? and who shall stand in his holy Place?</hi> And it is answered thus, <hi>He that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th clean Hands and a pure Heart, who hath not lift up his Soule to Vanity, nor sworn deceitfully, He shall receive the Blessing from the Lord, and Righteousnesse from the God of his Salvation.</hi> I am sure this is King <hi>Charles</hi> also, for it cannot be any of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that hath taken so many deceitfull Oaths, and certainly these Scriptures are in fulfil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing at this time.</p>
               <p>And one thing rejoiceth my heart, because it is suitable to my Faith, that some, by Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, have scraped <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> out of the Scots Cov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nant that hangs in Christ church, in <hi>London,</hi> which signifies to me, that either he never tooke it, or if he did, he doth repent it; that I am sure he may attaine to the second Magnitude, as I said before, for he is the Olive Branch, his name tells me that, besides hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> growth (being signified <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.12) from a low Condition to such a height of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minency, that he, under God, is able to doe it; for this word (Branch) is a Method taken from the Olive Branch, which the Dove brought to <hi>Noab,</hi> when he was in the Ark. <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.11. And as it was no small joy to the Father of the World then, to finde by the Branch, that the Water was abated from off the face of the earth; so it will be no little joy to the King, when he is proclaimed by the Lord Protector, and to see the violence of his people against him abated; therefore you have
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114594:28"/>
                  <hi>Ieremy,</hi> when he speaks of the Churches delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, saith he, <hi>I will raise unto</hi> David <hi>a righteous Branch, and a King shall reigne and prosper,</hi> Jer. 24.5. Mark first a <hi>Branch,</hi> and then a <hi>King;</hi> and in <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. saith he, <hi>I will bring my Serv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt the Branch, and I will remove the iniquity of that Land in one day,</hi> that is, when his Highnesse shall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the King; and <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.12, 13. saith he, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Man, whose name is the Branch,</hi> speaking as if some great person did slight him: and then tells you in the words following, what he shall doe, and that the Counsell of Peace shall be betweene the King and Him.</p>
               <p>And if we look back upon the time past, we shall finde, that the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liament called by his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse the last Somer, is called the Mount of Olives, or of <hi>Oliver, Zach.</hi> 14.4.5. And as that Mount is said to cleave in the middst, the one part toward the East, and the other toward the West, that there was a great Valley between; so you know that Parliament was divided equally in the midst, and broke asunder, parting one from the other in Minde, so farre as the East is from the West: And what flying away upon it was from the one side and from the other, and all against the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, as if there were a Valy between, to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st in hope of some better things to follow; the Text tells you, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. and we see it fulfilled among us, I beseech you conside<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it.</p>
               <p>But some man will say, Why doe you account the Protector to be the Branch, for the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes did interpret the Branch to be Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ist Jesus? What the Church saith, I say also; Christ is all in all, yet more properly, since we make a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>weene the Tree and its Branches: Truly we must take Christ by his own interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114594:28"/> to be the Tree that gives to the Branches life and being; so Christ calls himselfe the Vine, and his Discipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the Branches, <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. and St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls him the Olive-tree, and his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the Branches, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16, 17, 18, &amp;c. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Christ is not, being distinguished, this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Branch, but he is the Root that beares it. Againe, I pray observe the Text, saith he, <hi>I will raise unto David a righteous Branch: Ier.</hi> 23.5. And againe, saith he, <hi>I cause the Branch of Righteousnesse to grow up unto David,</hi> Jer. 33.15. Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ist is called the Son of <hi>David,</hi> and the Seed of <hi>David, Mat.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k</hi> 12.35. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2 8. and not a Son <hi>unto</hi> David, or a Seed <hi>unto</hi> David; which word (unto) beares another interpretation, as you see it doth, <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Unto us a Child is Borne, Unto us a Son is Given.</hi> And as this doth not argue, that he is properly our Sonne, but that he is the Sonne of God, given to us to be our Saviour: So in like manner, where it is said, <hi>I will raise a Branch unto David;</hi> it does not argue, that this Branch came of <hi>David,</hi> as Christ did, but it argues, that it is given to <hi>David,</hi> or to the King to help him; which King is signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied many times in Scripture, under that notion of <hi>David.</hi> And againe, this Branch must be (on) whose name significantly is the Branch of Olives, <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.12, 13. and he must be knowne by his G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>owth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Actions to be the Branch, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. for he shall remove the iniquity off the Land in one day: and what is the iniquity of this Nation, but their keeping of K <hi>Charls</hi> from his Right in it, And who can remove that, and do him right bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Oliver Grumwell</hi> and his Councell? And wherefore were they preserved and exalted, but to doe so glorious a piece of justice, that might make them delightfull to God, famous in the world, and crowne them for ever, as you see, <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.14.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:114594:29"/>
               <p>For my part I must be for his Highnesse the Lord Protector, because I see God is for him, hath appointed him for our good, that truly I dare not speak against him, as you know that have converse with me, I never did, but still told you, that he is the man that God hath appointed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store the Church to its former Glory, and also the King and Kingdome, in a Vision, as you have it in my Book called the <hi>Echo,</hi> seen 1637. when I was at the Gatehouse, <hi>Westminster,</hi> Prison I was charged not to touch the Olives: And this was many yeares before I heard of <hi>Oliver Cromwell;</hi> and these Olives in the said Book; I doe interpret to be a Royall Generation, appointed of God to help the King and to joyne in affinite with him; but if Gods wayes are refused, who can expect a Blessing from him? Truly if you doe it is in vaine.</p>
               <p>I do wonder at the foolishnesse of these Plotters, who would not obey my VOICE, for I gave them warning in my last Book, p. 27. not to meddle with such things: yet, as reports goe, they would needes Kill the Lord Protector, and Proclaime the King. Alas, poore silly men, if they had done such a thing, and proclaimed the King, what would they have been the better? Could not the Councell immediately have chosen another, that should have been worse against the Kings party? And would not all the people rose against the Plotters speedily, and destroyed them shamefully? No, it had been bttter for them, if they had sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prised the person of his Highnesse, not to hurt him, but to have been as carefull to preserve him, as if they found a Jewell of the highest value, and to keep him from hurt as the apple of their eye; for having the authority, the people upon his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:114594:29"/> had come in unto them, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell too; for they could not have chosen another Protector: if they had, he declaring for the King it had been to no purpose, than for the Plotters to make his Highnesse's peace with the King; and if the King would not have hearkened to them, for to stand for his Highnesse to the death, rather than a haire of his head should fall. And they thus seeking not for bloud, God had given a blessing to their endeavours for good, and all would have joyned to them; therefore I count them no Protestants that will stirre upon any other account; and I know, whosoever doth it, they shall be destroyed, for such plots are bloudy, foolish, and hatefull to any Christian, or true Protestant; and let none adhere unto them upon paine of damnation, I charge them not meddle.</p>
               <p>To kill a man of Warre (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.8.) treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rously, was so hatefull to <hi>David,</hi> that when <hi>Joab</hi> his Sisters Son, chief Captain of his army, and one that helped him much, being always true unto him, had killed <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amasa,</hi> two chief Captaines that fought against <hi>David</hi> for <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Absolom;</hi> he could not forget it, but at his death-bed, gives a charge to <hi>Solomon</hi> concerning <hi>Joab,</hi> to cut him off for his treachery in killing those two gallant men, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.55. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.12, 13, 14, 15, 16: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.6. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.25. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.27, 28, 29, 30. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.5, 6.29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34. And <hi>David</hi> had such respect to such men, that though <hi>Amasa</hi> was chief Captain in the head of <hi>Absaloms</hi> Rebellion against him, yet afterward <hi>David</hi> forgave him all; and with that preferree him to be Captaine of the house of <hi>Iudah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.3. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.4. his nearest relation. Here you see what esteeme <hi>David</hi> had of such men, as his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:114594:30"/> Highnesse the Lord <hi>Cromwell,</hi> is, that, though they had acted never so high against him, yet he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gives them, preferres them, avengeth their bloud treacherously spilt upon his chiefe Captaine, he being also his own Siste<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Son. He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is an Example for King <hi>Charles</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let me tell you plainly, these Plots against the one, and against the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, are so many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings from God to the King and Protector, that they should agree; for we have a Proverb among us, saying, <hi>A Pitcher that goeth to the well often, comes to be broken at last:</hi> therefore let them take heed, lest their division, which is the cause of spil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling so many an innocent righteous mans bloud, <hi>Psal.</hi> 9.12. <hi>Psal</hi> 116 15. bring the plots against them to effect, and they be disappointed of their hopes, by some other that shall enjoy it; I say this in faithfulnesse to them both, because it is many times seen, that while two strive for the Ball, the third comes and gets it away f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om them both, and then their Controversie endeth, and they are Friends againe. Truly his Highness the Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, hath most reason to heare me, if not for Himselfe, yet for his Families sake; for if a time should come that we have another Protector, and that he make peace and b ing in the King, what then should become of his Highnesse his family, Judge you? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. But I have a strong belief, though I thus speak, that his Highness is so wise that it will never come to that passe, and that he will redeeme his precious time, <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.15, 16, 17. while the Sun shine upon him.</p>
               <p>Oh, saith some men, His Highnesse can never bring in the King, and make peace with him, for he hath taken so many Oaths to the contrary.</p>
               <p>It is true, that is a great stumbling-block in the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:114594:30"/> way: But we may say thus much to that, Suppose a young man should make himselfe sure to foure maids, the one after another, and promise all of them, Marriage, as sometimes such things are in the world; and at last, he in conscience begin to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider which of them he had best to take to be his wife, and which oath or promise to keep. I believe you will say, and the Holy spirit will second you, that he ought to return to his first Love, and to keep his first Vow, and to fulfill his first Promise; by marrying her to whom he was first ingaged. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4, 5. The case is the same, though his Highness and others have taken so many Oaths, yet I am confident, the first Oaths, they took were for the Church of England, and for the King and his Seed; Let them look to these Oaths▪ and now at last keep them, if they look to have a cleare Conscience, and repent concerning the rest, so shall they be blessed, and have comfort at the last.</p>
               <p>Others say, That the late King was so confident upon the Lord Protector and Lord <hi>Fairfaxes</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises, that he told to some of his friends a little before his death, saying, If they had souls, he should not die, for said the King, I have their souls in pawn for it: therefore if the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor intended any good for the King, Why did he suffer him to be put to death?</p>
               <p>I answer, you know that the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> had as much reason to confide in the late King, and did confide in him, thought himself sure, and God knowes the King wanted not a mind to save him, but he wanted a power to save him from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent cry of the people, stirred up by cruell instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who thirsted for his bloud: And the Kings case was the same. This the Lord Protector wanted not the mind, but the power to save the King; for
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:114594:31"/> now there is a terrible violent Army stirred up by bloudy, and cruell instruments, who thirsted for the Kings bloud; for the Cry of the common people in such a case, is like the cry of a Dragon, that hath his breath from hell, which by violence, against all reason, will condemne the most righteous of men: you see Christ Jesus was condemned by the Cry of the multitude against him, which multitude was stirred up to doe it, by the high Priests and Elders. Mat. 27.20.21.22.23. So the Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters and their factious Parliament-men stirr'd up the multitude to cry against <hi>Strafford,</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <hi>Laud,</hi> and all the rest of the good Bishops, with other precious men, to have their bloud, which bloud cries to God, <hi>Luke.</hi> 18.7 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11.</p>
               <p>And did not those cruell ones stirre up the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and all the sectaries to cry so for the late Kings bloud, that it was impossible for any man, though his power had been never so great, to deliver him out of their hands? Therefore blame not his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse for that: and I say this for the Lord <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> that he could not say to our Soveraigne as <hi>Pilate</hi> said to our Saviour <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.10. for he could not help the King, al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hough he had stood to the death for him; for as holy <hi>Aaron,</hi> to keep his station and the people in some order, was forced to comply with their humors in <hi>Moses</hi> absence; <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1, 2, 3, 4. so also many good men now, though unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, were forced to comply in wic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed acts with the humou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the people, who, untill they smart for it, commonly being stirred up by <hi>Korah, Dathan;</hi> and <hi>Abirams</hi> seed, are set on mischief, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. as <hi>Aaron</hi> saith to <hi>Moses, Exod.</hi> 32.22, 23, 24, 25. <hi>Thou knowest the people, that they are set on mischief:</hi> And one was saying in discourse, merily, said he, <hi>Israel</hi> had
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:114594:31"/> of <hi>Aaron</hi> but a Calf for their Plate brought in to him, but the Presbyterians gave us a Bull for all our Plate brought into Guild hall, and elsewhere; and as when <hi>Moses</hi> was in the Mount, communing with God about the Law, the Devil was among the people to bring a Calf for them to their ruine: <hi>Ex.</hi> 31.18 <hi>Ex</hi> 32.1. So in like manner, while the K. was gone up to the House of Lords, to cosult about wholsom Laws for the Kingdom, the Presbyterians were b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inging forth a Bull for us to our ruine; But, under God, my hope is, that his Highnesse will restore the King &amp; Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> again to be more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than ever it was, and that the people now will be satisfied therein, having tasted and filled themselves with their owne folly, so that they are weary of it.</p>
               <p>And now to conclude, Let none take exception against me, for what I say against Independants, Anabaptists, Presbyterians, or any other, I say it with grief to see a cause. And as I speak to my owne children, whom I delight to see weepe for their faults, but cannot indure to see them bleed, so I speak to all with the bowels of compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for I know God will destroy this Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it repent and embrace that way which was set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led among us, for there is none more hatefull to God, than those that slight such mercies, the things of the world are but triffl s, <hi>Israel</hi> onely had the law, <hi>Israel</hi> sl gh s it, therefore <hi>Israel</hi> hath been punished above all Nations on the earth, <hi>Amos.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9 11, 12, 13, 14, And at this day are in slavery, so scattered that we cannot properly call them a N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion or people, for refusing Gods special mercie: And yet they have a more particular promise than any people under heaven, now if they be so severely punished, yet preserved because of the promise, how then shall this Nation escape a totall destinction, who have sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ghted the like mercies, except they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:114594:32"/>
               <head>Let us Pray,</head>
               <p>O Lord, the hearts of all men are in thine hand, especially of Kings and Rulers, and thou turnest them as the Rivers of Water, wheresoever it pleaseth thee: O turne the heart of King <hi>Charles</hi> to the Lord <hi>Protector</hi> and his Councell, and turne their hearts to his MAJESTY, that they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united in Love one towards another, may build againe thy Sanctuary, and set up thy holy Worship among us, and turne the hearts of all to be obedient unto them: We know that we all have rebelled against thee, and slighted thy mercies; therefore hast thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Candlestick, and taken the Glory from us. Lord, pardon our Sins, be favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thy People, by restoring unto us thy true Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ship againe, that we may see as we have seen, the goings in the San<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tuary, and reverence thy glorious and dreadfull Name there, and turne not againe to folly. Lord let us consider how we have wand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed all this while, where there is no path, like a lost She<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p and mingled our Bloud with our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; and yet such is the spirit which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, that after this long searching and wandering to finde nothing but emptinesse, confusion, and destruction; we are hardened
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:114594:32"/> against the faith once delivered to the Saints, and established among us, and are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded to returne to thee. Turn us (ô Lord) and we shall be turned: Cause thy Face to shine upon us and we shall be saved. Lord, if thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> restore unto us thy holy Worship againe, we vow, through thy help, we will walk perfectly therein and adorne it with so holy a life, that all the world shall acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be the onely way to salvation. Grant this (O heavenly Father) for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Jesus Christ our Bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssed Saviour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114594:33"/>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:114594:33"/>
            <head>The Authors Vindication, concerning the Year <hi>1653.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEloved, our good God at all times, when he had a special work to do for his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he never failed to shew himself in an extraordinary manner, and by signes &amp; won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to confirm his truth, yet for all that the blind Worlding never had the grace to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it: as you may evidently see by the Scripture what excellent visible signes was shown by <hi>Moses:</hi> but <hi>Pharoah</hi> having the world in his heart could not believe it; yea many of <hi>Israel</hi> murmured also. <hi>Exodus</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. <hi>Psal.</hi> 106.7.</p>
            <p>What a wonderfull work of God was it, to behold the Sun and Moon stand still in the time of <hi>Josuah? Jos.</hi> 10.11, 12, 13. To see the dead raised to life? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.32, 36. To see Iron swim? <hi>Kings</hi> 6.6. To see the Meal and the Oyl increase? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.11, 12, 13, 14, 15. To see so many Vessels of Oyl filled from one? 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. To see the Sun return ten degrees back in the dayes of <hi>Hezekiah?</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.11. To see the 3. holy Men to come out of the flaming furnace alive? <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.26. To see innocent <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> come out of the Lions Den alive? <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.23. And many other signes which God shewed in those times; yet few then laid such things to heart, but still rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led against the truth: as the generations fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing did also in their times against those mighty signes, and wonderfull works done
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:114594:34"/> by our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, and his holy Apostles, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3, 4. yea God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failed from the beginning to this time, but he sent Prophets in time of need to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phesie, and work miracles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.34, 35, 36. though the blind leaders of the blind <hi>Math.</hi> 15, 14. have always denyed them, and doe deny them to this day; fasly affirming that now prophesying is ceased.</p>
            <p>But the People of God ought to believe the truth, that there hath been Prophets continually in the Church from the Apostles time to this day: and that God at the last will deliver his people not in an ordinary way, but in a miraculous way, he will send down fire from Heaven to devour their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries <hi>Revel.</hi> 20, 9. And therefore those Princes who despise prophecying of all men are in a most miserable condition, because their unfidelity will not suffer them to take warning, when they are told by a true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Spirit, that there is evill against them, and prevent it: neither when any good is on their lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; they have not faith to believe it, though it be told them, nor to take the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the time appointed for them to obtain it; But such as regard prophesying are always successfull in their actings, for they believe; and when evil is pronounced against them, they turn away the wrath of God by their repentance, fasting and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and when good is prophesied to them, they are not negligent in doing what lyeth in them to bring it to passe, and these things have been verified in our days as truly as in the days of old.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:114594:34"/>
            <p>I believe that at this time I am scandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by many people, who did expect the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent King <hi>Charls</hi> coming to <hi>Brittain</hi> in a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant manner before the 25 of last <hi>March,</hi> I had rather be Scandalized than Idolized, as some I am very confident would have done me, if such a thing had come to passe: In their sence, had they according to my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection forsaken their pride, vanities and sins, &amp; been prepared &amp; fitted to receive so great a blessing, they had obtained it; And who can tell but that the King came hear in a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant manner before that time was expired on purpose to fulfill my words, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably without any molestation returned back again, as those three worthiest did, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.14, 15, 16. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>And it was reported for a truth, that the King was here in <hi>February</hi> last, and that there was a Plot intended, but if there was a plot I believe it was without his consent, for I am confident he had rather chuse to lose his Crown, than to obtain it by a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssacre, to have innocent blood upon his House, but he will try it out in the high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Field with his adversaries, he jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that those who will oppose him in arms, will bring their blood upon their own heads at last.</p>
            <p>But me thinks I hear (as I have heard some that were of the Kings Servants proudly say) Dost thou think that the King will hazard his person and come to <hi>England</hi> to fullfill thy words? I dare say he regards thee not, nor thinks of thy words, neither did he ever send any to tell thee, that he would come to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> upon such account.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:114594:35"/>
            <p>I answer truly it may be so as they say, for they know the King better then I do, they being his Servants, and that I am mistaken in him, as they averr, yet I think they are not of his Council, nor of the wisest of his Friends that reports him to be thus minded: and suppose they are both, what I said in that Case is uncertain; but of this I am sure, If he had Come in with a few men, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the dissolution of the long-sitting Parliament, or upon the dissolution of the last Parliament, so called, and Declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght have had recover'd his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms again to him with much ease: for in the intervene, while the people were in uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and distraction, they would have ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally arose with him, and had set him on his throne before this time; but where wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and valour is wanting, such things can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done: yet what need hath he to be affraid, who at several times had such great deliverances? <hi>David</hi> going out against <hi>Goliah</hi> said from his experience, with a further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that he had in God, <hi>The Lord that hath delivered me from the Lion and the Bear, will deliver me from this Philistine. Caesar</hi> also from a confidence that he had in a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenish Prophecy which spake of him: He being at Sea, there arose a great Tempest, which continued, insomuch that the Master of the Ship and Mariners fainted, giving up themselves as dead men; but <hi>Caesar</hi> couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously stands up, and saith to them, <hi>Be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid, ye shall not be cast away at this time, for here is</hi> Caesar <hi>and all his fortune, and you know how he conquered the World:</hi> God never fails the Faithfull.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:114594:35"/>
            <p>But what, as they say, if King <hi>Charls</hi> doth not believe what I declare concerning him? Then how can I or any other believe that he shall enjoy the the promise? for my part I have no certain ground to believe that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth what I have declared concerning him to be true; for had he believed it, he had either by Letter, or a word of mouth by some of his Servants, signified that he tooke notice of it, and that he gave God thanks for his goodnesse to him in his trouble, by rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing me up to show so much for him, and to keep up the hearts of his friends in every place, and to daunt his Enemies with such weapons that are more terrible to them than a sword: And truly he had good reason to send me some token of his acceptation, when he saw, according to my prophecying, the dissolution of the Parliament, and the great alteration in the Kingdom since in order to his entrance, to the Comfort of his Friends, and the converting of many Thousands that were opposite to him, to be on his side: so that there was nothing wanting to Compleat my prophecying, but his comming in afore the time was expired, according to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples expectation, which neglect of his spoyled all. Again I say, had he come in, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence would have been so prevalent, that he should have found God would not have fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him in performance of his restoration, and time lost is not to be regained, except God work a miracle for that end, and call back the time again.</p>
            <p>Let no man think that I say this from any ambitious desire I have that the King should
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:114594:36"/> take notice of me; but I desire to know a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony of his faith in those things God hath given me to hold forth concerning him, that I might with full assurance present my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God for him, and until I have such an evidence from his Majestie, I shall stand in do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bt of him, least I have bestowed on him my labour in vain <hi>Galath.</hi> 4, 11, 20. For if his Majestie be perswaded as many others are falsly perswaded, that there is no true Prophets now; then can he never expect the things promised in the Prophesie set out by me, but some other that hath faith will snatch his right from him, as <hi>Jacob</hi> did from <hi>Esau,</hi> though the blessing by me is intended for him; as <hi>Isaack</hi> intended it for <hi>Esau,</hi> but <hi>Jacobs</hi> pollicie carried it away, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25, 34, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27, 36. and God was well pleased with <hi>Jacob</hi> for it, because he esteemed the things of God which <hi>Esau</hi> sold and despised: Therefore saith God of such, <hi>Them that will honour me, I will honour, And they that despise me shall be lightly esteemed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2, 30.</p>
            <p>Therefore I would have his Majestie to consider, that though he and his Peers, Counsel, and Ministers, look upon me as a poor inconsiderable man, yet I know through the power that God hath indued me withal, by his Word I am more able to do him good, if he can believe it than all his Friends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides; because the Spirit of Prophesie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all the Wheels or generalty of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to act and pray for him, specially when it is beleeved, and my Books and prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie have been so really fulfilled, that those
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:114594:36"/> who before would not be perswaded from Scripture nor from reason that there is any Prophets in our days, have since been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of their Errors by the very actions which they saw come to passe, according to my Prophesie, soe that now his influence is greater than ever it was upon the Nations, through the faith they have in my sayings: I had not spoken thus had not some of the Kings Friends or rather his Enemies moved me to doubt as abovesaid, yet am I not the lesse confident of his fidelity upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, however I have said thus much that ye might be faithfull.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Caesar</hi> notwithstanding his Faith as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bovesaid, at last wanted it when he was told by a Poet what day he should die, had he believed and taken warning then, he might had prevented the Senators plot against him, and been faved from a violent death, <hi>without faith it is impossible to please God</hi> Heb. 11, 6. and he doth not send Prophets into the World for to be mocked by foolish men, but for to save men from dangers, for the greatest Prophet of all can doe no good by his prophesying to an unbelieving Nation; Christ Jesus himself could not doe mighty works in his own Country, because they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided him and believed him not <hi>Mark</hi> 6, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. But <hi>Peter</hi> his Servant, being in repute and believed, cureth the People with his very shadow as he passeth by them, <hi>Acts</hi> 5, 14, 15, 16. Here you see the power of Faith in the hearers and beholders of a Prophet is that which heals them <hi>Acts</hi> 28, 26, 27.</p>
            <p>Therefore Christ Jesus saith unto his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:114594:37"/> Messengers, <hi>He that heareth you heareth me, and he that despiseth you desp seth me, and he that despiseth me, despiseth him that sent me, Luke</hi> 10.3.16. Again he saith to them, <hi>He that receiveth you, receiveth me, and he that receiveth me, receiveth him that sent me, Matth.</hi> 10.40. and all this is spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning the Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ets and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, but chiefly it concerneth the Prophets, for in the Verse following saith he, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.41. <hi>He that receiveth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, shall receive a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ophets Reward:</hi> And this word surely is sufficient, if they were not blind, to convince all those that say we must expect no Prophets now; for why should Christ speak of Receiving a Prophet, and of the great benefit to those that would receive him, if there were not a Prophet to be sent, it were a vain thing to say Receive a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and not to send one: But we know Christs words are not in vain, nor the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, who saith <hi>Despise not prophecying,</hi> 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 5.20. And again sheweth, That Prophets are a distinct order of Men, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from Pastors and Teachers, to continue in the Church, so long as the Ministry, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>But they ignorantly will Object, saying, <hi>We have no Apostles now, that Function is cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to be: Therefore why may not that Function called Prophets cease to be also?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I answer,</hi> A Bishop and an Apostle is one and the self-same Office, for speaking of <hi>Judas</hi> who was one of the Twelve Apostles, saith he, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.20. <hi>Let another take his Bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick.</hi> Hence you may see that the Apostles
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:114594:37"/> were Bishops, and we have Bishops in the Church of Christ: But ask a Presbyterian hireling who is a Bishop, or a Prophet, or an Evangelist, or a Preacher, or a Pastor, or Teacher, or any spiritual Function whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Scripture makes mention of? he will tell you, That he hath all that in himself: Just as if a petty Constable should tell you, That he can doe as much as a King or any of his Officers can doe, in matter of Ruling.</p>
            <p>But some Man will say, <hi>What is a Prophets Reward? What can a Prophet do for us, if we receive him? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, what can he doe against us, if we despise him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I answer,</hi> A Prophet hath power to Root up, and to destroy Kingdoms and Nations, and hath power to plant them in, and to build them again, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.10. If they will hear and receive the Prophet, and believe the Word of God shewed to them by him, and acordingly every one turn from his evil way, then shall he build them up, and plant them: But if they refuse to hear him, and despise him, he shall Root them out, and Cast them down, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7, 8, 9, 10. So that you see the Prophet hath his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with him, to give unto all according to their works, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. And it is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as some ignorant persons would have it, which say, That my Prophesie, if it be a true Prophesie, must come to passe for their good, though they continue in their sins. But there is no such matter delivered to them by me; for Gods mercy doth not extend it self to such wilfull impenitent Sinners that hold forth such an argument, and are resolved
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:114594:38"/> not to be reformed according to godlinesse, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12.</p>
            <p>And now let me tell you of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in plain terms why you were not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stored the last year according to my Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
            <p>The Reason is because the Lord Protector and his party had more respect to my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy than you had, and believed it more than you did, therefore he and his party ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained what you should have received had you believed. The second reason is because for a testimony of your faith you did not turn unto God with all your hearts to serve him, and to call upon him, and leave your sins and vanities, as ye were directed by my Writings, then had all things come to pass as I said in the time expected; therefore God doth add year to year <hi>Isa.</hi> 29, 1. to bring you to amend your lives: For as I said in my book called the <hi>Eccho,</hi> you must not expect such a voluptuous Court and Kingdome, abounding with pride, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and licentiousnesse, as we had here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore in <hi>England,</hi> because God doth all things for the better, and not for the worse to the Children of men, for that your suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, blood and war is not in vain by Gods account, and he that learns to amend his life by these things, and strives to be most perfect, shall doubtlesse obtain the greatest glory hereafter, when all things shall be restored, and that Kingdom come.</p>
            <p>But some Man will say; <hi>When will that be? for we find that you have failed in the time perfixed for the Kings coming in, which we
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:114594:38"/> expected before the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> March <hi>last past, or the end of the year</hi> 1653.</p>
            <p>Truly what I have spoken concerning the 25 of <hi>March</hi> by peoples urging of me, I will not stand to vindicate my self from that, for upon such occasion of needless inquiry, In answering the peoples demands suddenly by word of mouth, having no time to weigh and consider my words I might err therein.</p>
            <p>But that which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave delivered by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, I always weighed and considered the grounds of all I set down, and being serious in my meditations, I had a dependencie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Providence of the all seeing God; that he would guide me with his Spirit of Truth in what I wrote, having always the Scripture before me to search and inquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; Therefore I am confident that what I have written, if you take it wholy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided you shall find it a real truth, As for example in my book called the <hi>Eccho,</hi> I say upon the exposition of <hi>Trust w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> Prophesie, that the King shall come in, in 1653, but withall in the latter end of the same book I tell you, that if you did not turn wholy to God, things might goe otherwise with you; and you know Gods promise is partly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally to the Children of men, for it is not suitable to his holinesse and justice, that he should build up an unholy Generation, that doth not regard his Commandements and strive to keep them.</p>
            <p>And for 1653, some have told me about <hi>Christmas</hi> last saying, now we find you to be a true Prophet, we have a King, the Lord Protector is no lesse than a King, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:114594:39"/> now the God of these Countries, as the late King <hi>Charls</hi> was, why may not he be called <hi>Charls Steward,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shazzar, Dan.</hi> 4.8. and then your Phrophesie is really fulfilled.</p>
            <p>But these are the Conjectures of Men which see no further: I have as much reason to speak for the <hi>Lord Protector</hi> as any man, and I have, and do speak for him in Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course, more than any doth; besides, by Gods assistance, I shall strive to vindicate those two Families, yet I most stand for the interest of God in <hi>Charles Steward,</hi> for he is the Bridegroom: who hath more influence (through Gods gift) upon the world, than any Man hath, And I am much concerned with him, in regard I have declared so high for him, and my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings are gone over all the Earth; and they be so blessed, that I cannot call them back, because that in him, now, is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of all Nations for their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and eternal Peace and Rest, that they have their faith fixed in God; and one <hi>Charls,</hi> do believe that he will bring to passe what I have spoken concerning King <hi>Charls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, when there is a business of so great concernment don in the World, for the advancement of Gods glory, and Comfort of his people, God will appear by something in it more than ordinary to the view of all the world; As for Example, When God by <hi>Iosuah</hi> brought the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> to that terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strial Rest of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was but a figure or type of the Celestial Rest of the Church, The Sun (being the most glorious Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:114594:39"/> in the Heavens) stood still for a whole day, that all the world m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ght see it. <hi>Ios.</hi> 10.13. Also in the days of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> to confirm that the King should come into the House of the Lord, upon the third day, God caused the Sun to go back ten degrees, 2 <hi>K ngs</hi> 20.5, 8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>Isa.</hi> 38.8. And now for as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance to you that God will bring King <hi>Charles</hi> to his Kingdom and People again, he will not cause the Sun to stand still only for a day, nor for to return ten degrees from that it was gone down by the Sun-dyal of <hi>Ahaz:</hi> but he will cause the Sun to return back a whole year, from that it is gone down by the account of all the Vulgar in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by all accounts they looke upon this year to be the year 1654. but I shall through Gods assistance make it appear, really, and not contrary to the <hi>English</hi> account rightly understood, that the year 1653 is not expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red until <hi>Christmass</hi> next: for we begin the year of Christ at the 25 <hi>March,</hi> neither do we date the year from his Birth, but from his Conception; so that there is a mystery in our <hi>English</hi> account that few or none did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it afore now, because they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded by the Almanack-makers setting of the Golden Number, and the Dominical Letter wrong; for they set that Number and Letter to the year 1654. which should be set by right to the year 1653. And this hath been their Custome time out of mind, so that the People thinks the same year which begins from the Birth at <hi>Christmass,</hi> to be the same year which begins from the Concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the 25 of <hi>March</hi> following: making
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:114594:40"/> as if Christ were born three moneths before he was conceived in his Mothers womb.</p>
            <p>And this is a <hi>Romish</hi> Error, that to this day remaineth among us, for if we doe but consider the truth of the matter, we shall find that we doe not only differ from their Account ten days, but we also differ in the number of the years from Christs birth a whole year, for by their account last <hi>Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> begin the year 1654, from Christs birth, but our account, doth not begin 1654, from the birth until next <hi>Christmas,</hi> so that you see here the Sun is a whole year and ten days turn'd back, by the providence of God, from that it is gone down by the <hi>Romish</hi> Dyal, or account, which Dyal is taken for currant by all the vulgar in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet the learned question it very much, the Bishop of <hi>Armath, Usher</hi> by name, saith in his Chronology, that they are a year or more out, in the account from Christs birth; And <hi>Clavis Apocalyptica,</hi> who proves all by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, saith, that the 6000 years from the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world, doe expire at the 1655 years of Christ, as ye have it page 25. and page 130 of that Book: And now the Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers saith, it is but 5603 years since the Creation of the world; so that <hi>Clavis</hi> and they differ in their accounts from the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 395 years at least.</p>
            <p>Thus you see the Computation is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and much disputed of among the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; insomuch that a most learned pious ancient Divine advised me not to rely upon the certainty of the common accounts of the years from Christs birth; for, said he, your
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:114594:40"/> Visions which have proved so infallible hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, are more certain truth than our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; therefore (said he) since God hath revealed to you by Visions, That <hi>Charls Steward</hi> shall come to his throne, and enjoy his 3. Kingdoms again before the year 1653 be expired: that year the King is restored into his own again, questionlesse is the year 1653; whereupon I answered him, saying, that I found the English account, as I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood it, to be true; for, said I, it proved true according to the time I set down in my first Book for the dissolution of the Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Therefore I say, if it be true as our English account saith, That it was 1653 years compleat from the Conception of Christ to the last 25 of <hi>March,</hi> and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan 1654. doubtlesse it cannot be 1653 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat from his birth, and begin 1654. untill next <hi>Christmas:</hi> for the Conception must needs be nine months before the birth.</p>
            <p>And to prove that the Church of <hi>England</hi> do begin the year of our only blessed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jesus Christ, at the 25 of <hi>March:</hi> And that they verifie that day to be the day of Christs conception, look into the Calander of the Church, that is in the Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-book, which was established by a general consent, and you shall find these words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing recorded therein,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note also, that the year of our Lord beginneth the</hi> 25 <hi>of</hi> March, <hi>the same day supposed to be the first day, upon which the World was created, and the same day when Christ was conceived in the womb of the Virgin</hi> Mary.</p>
            <p>Yet this is an error in the English ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:114594:41"/> to reckon the years and time of Christs age from his conception; for where doth the Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iptures, or any History, count mens age, but from their Birth; Therefore ought we to reckon Christs years as he is a man, that is from his Birth: for as he is God he is from all Eternity, there is no reckoning of his years.</p>
            <p>But I am so far from judging our Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors ignorant, that I believe they began the year at the 25 of <hi>March,</hi> wittingly fo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeing then, what should be done in these our dayes, and that when all our expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons failed us, we should have need of nine moneths more added by Gods Providence to our account, for to bring forth a glorious King in <hi>Seon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Astrologers account, if they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand it right, do not disagree with me; for I hold that it is not 1653 years compleat from the birth of Christ until next <hi>Christmas,</hi> because we according to the <hi>Julian</hi> account, begin our year the first of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> and we call it such a year of Christ, not that it is compleat, but because he was born in such a <hi>Julian</hi> year, when there remained of it but seven dayes; that is, from <hi>December</hi> 25. to the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st of <hi>January;</hi> so that by our account they at first began his second year, when he was but eight dayes old, that within Eight dayes after his first was compleat, they wrote it his third year, and so went on until now.</p>
            <p>Thus the Astrologers goes on, and some of them are ingenious men: yet since they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to follow the Wisemen, <hi>Matth:</hi> 2.1. I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:114594:41"/> would have them honour Christ, as the Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men did, who acknowledged him to be a King at his birth, saying, <hi>Where is he that is born King of the Jews? Matth.</hi> 2.1, 2. and henceforth not to give <hi>Julius Caesar</hi> the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour belonging to Jesus Christ; but to alter their account, and to begin his year from his Birth, that all might understand the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count: for, I say, so long as the account goes on as it doth, the Kingdom of Christ is not acknowledged by them, but <hi>Caesars</hi> Kingdom, or fourth Monarchy contiues still; Therefore I say to you Astrologers, If you be the friends of Christ Jesus, let the Kingdom of Christ, or fifth Monarchy begin now, else he will destroy you for this very Cause, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.27. <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.15. And I say likewise to the Lawyers, let them Date all the Records of the Nation according to that; and let all men also have their Writings newly engros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed according to that account of Christ: otherwise they shall lose all they have, and others shall obey and enjoy their possessions.</p>
            <p>And least some dull heads be uncapable to understand the matter in hand, to make it yet more clear, I will state the Case thus.</p>
            <p>Suppose the 100 year, less or more of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, that <hi>Caesar Augustus, Luke</hi> 2.1. began his Reign the first of <hi>January,</hi> and that Christ was born 25 of <hi>Decem.</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the same first year of <hi>Augustus</hi> his reign.</p>
            <p>By that account we grant it was upon the first day of <hi>January</hi> last past, 1653 years com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, since <hi>Augustus</hi> began his Reign: yet by the same account you see it is clear, that it is not 1653 years compleat from Christs birth, until the 25 of <hi>December</hi> next.</p>
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:114594:42"/>
            <p>And you see by the account at 25 of <hi>March,</hi> and the <hi>Julian</hi> account, which both agree, that it is not 1653 compleat, until 25 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> next.</p>
            <p>And now I have made clear unto you by what account I go, that you might see the year, 1653. is not expired until next <hi>Christ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> also to tell you, that there came out two sheets in my name, which are none of mine, The one is called, <hi>The Declaration of Arise Evans,</hi> and came out <hi>Febr.</hi> 7. 1653. The other came out <hi>Febr.</hi> 14. 1653. and is called, <hi>The great and bloudy Vision;</hi> both which sheets hath a great deal of my words taken out of my Books in them: but I do not use to write the same matter over again, and put it out in print; therefore be not deceived.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word concerning Astrology.</head>
               <p>ANd for the Astrologers I find them to be of a far more excellent, meek, ingenious wise-spirited men, than the proud Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Ministers; And that one Astrologer who wrote a little Book, called <hi>King Charles his Starre,</hi> hath clearly by Scripture confuted their annotation of the <hi>Bible,</hi> so far as it is against Astrology, that it plainly appears there is more of God in that man, than in all the English Presbyterian Ministers: It is true, I wrote something against the extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy of some men pretending to that <hi>science,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20. And specially against Mr. <hi>George Wharton,</hi> because of the two Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacks coming out in his name: but it seems he was wronged in it; for as a Friend of his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:114594:42"/> told me, he owns but one of them, which if he had declared so much, as Mr. <hi>Lilly did in the same Case,</hi> he had prevented me from writing any thing of that nature; <hi>neither after I wrote</hi> had I a mind to put it in print, <hi>until</hi> a Friend would need have it to print, <hi>pretending</hi> that if his <hi>Almanack</hi> was counterfeited, he knew who had done it, and mine coming forth upon it, would be a plea for him to right himself.</p>
               <p>Yet in what I wrote against them, I do not condemn their way no further than it was prohibited by the Law in the time of our late <hi>Kings,</hi> that is, their Casting of Nativities, their monethly prognosticating concerning States matters, their telling of fortunes, and of things that are lost, which things many times afterwards <hi>wounds the conscience</hi> of such as seek of them, that they fall to evil courses, and to <hi>despair:</hi> but for the use of their way in Physick aind Chirurgery, and the use of it, to show the nature of <hi>Plants</hi> and <hi>Seeds,</hi> &amp; when, where, and how to plant or sow, and for the ordering of Cattel: for to know the course of the year, the time of the Eclipse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Comets, Conjunction of Planets, with their judgment upon it, may be lawfull. But this I say, the <hi>Stars</hi> or Planets by their influence, as they ar <hi>signes,</hi> declare nothing concerning things to come, if they be rightly understood, but the same that the spirit of God declares by the <hi>Scripture</hi> also, for all the works of <hi>God</hi> are yea, &amp; not yea, and nay. Therefore I say its need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Astrologers, if they would be Prophets, <hi>diligently</hi> to search the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and not wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly to seek to set <hi>up</hi> Astrology above it.</p>
               <p>But I say the <hi>Science is lawfull,</hi> if it be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully used, and directs <hi>to God,</hi> if men use it as
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:114594:43"/> the <hi>Wise men</hi> did, for I find that they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>God</hi> by <hi>visions,</hi> as well as by that <hi>science,</hi> Mat. 2.12.16. and did obey him.</p>
               <p>Now for their casting of <hi>Nativities,</hi> this clearly confutes them, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esau</hi> was born in one minute, for <hi>Iacob</hi> had <hi>Esau</hi> by the heel, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25, 24, 25, 26. <hi>Hos.</hi> 12.3. yet we read of what different nature &amp; fortune they were, the one was beloved of God, the other was hated of him. <hi>Esau lived in pomp,</hi> and his Sons were <hi>Dukes,</hi> Gen. 36.18. and had 3 Wives, and but 5 Sons, and had much riches, but how he came by thē we know not; he lived as a Gent. and was given to hunting, and did not regard the things of God, <hi>he was a man of the field,</hi> and perhaps took by violence the most part of his riches, but <hi>Iacob</hi> feared <hi>God,</hi> and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what he served hard for: he had 4 Wives, and 12 Sons, and endured much hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for a long time, <hi>was a plain man, Gen.</hi> 25.27 <hi>Gen.</hi> 29. <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. If there be truth in casting Nativities, why should not these two men agree in their natures and fortunes?</p>
               <p>And what are the Astrologers <hi>but fools,</hi> to think that Astrology in it self is to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with true <hi>Divine Revelations</hi> by the only Spirit of God, which comes from the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> therfore let them be ashamed that mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for lucre sake use it, and let them be <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicld</hi> for Fools that seek after them, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. but for those that use it for the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and for the good of the Nations, let them be <hi>as the stars that turn many to righteousness,</hi> Dan. 12.3. yet we know the most excellent of that <hi>Science,</hi> I mean the <hi>Wise men of the East,</hi> Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.1. whom they say were Astrologers, came far short in knowledge to the poor Shepherds
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:114594:43"/> divine revelations, <hi>Lu.</hi> 2.8. for to the Wisemen by a <hi>Star</hi> was made known that <hi>Messiah</hi> was born, but they knew not exactly where he was born; for if they did, what need had they to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of <hi>Herod</hi> and the <hi>Priests,</hi> Mar. 2.2, 3, 4, 5, 6. neither knew they the exact time of his birth, for then, what need had <hi>Herod</hi> after he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the Wisemen the time of his birth, or what time the Star appeared? If they had told him the exact time, what need had <hi>Herod to kill all the Children frō two years old and under,</hi> Mar. 2.7.16. but God revealed to the Shepherds the day <hi>when</hi> Christ was born, and the City where Christ was born, saying, <hi>unto you is born this day in the City of</hi> David <hi>a Saviour, which is Christ the Lord:</hi> let this suffice to show their <hi>Science,</hi> when men attain to the highest knowledge of it, it is but an uncertain knowledg.</p>
               <p>And now I say to you Almanack makers: If you do not alter the account according to the abovesaid direction, I pronounce you to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to the <hi>Lord Iesus Christ,</hi> and his <hi>kingdom:</hi> And I humbly desire his <hi>Highnes the L. Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and his <hi>Honourable Council,</hi> as they tender the honour of <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> and seek his kingdom to come unto us, and expect a blessing by it, That they suffer not the heathenish account to continue any longer among us, but to stop all Almanacks that do not begin as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said from the birth of <hi>Christ:</hi> for that is the first step to the 5th Monarchy, or kingdom of <hi>Christ;</hi> for you see there was a time appointed <hi>for Christ to take his great power, &amp; reign upon the earth,</hi> Rev. 11.15, 16, 17, 18, 19. and that time is come, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Now the Lord of peace himself give you peace always, by all means, the Lord be with you all,</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>ARISE EVANS.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:114594:44"/>
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THey that are most vicious of the <hi>Kings</hi> party, are the most hasty to be delivered, and to have the King come in; and they are them which hinder him from coming, for they cannot leave their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporate swearing and ryoting, and will any judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial man think that God who hath brought a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon us for such sins, will remove the same, and restore us again, until we leave our sins? No, God brought the Judgement, either to mend us, or end us, for them that think <hi>to doe evil that good may come thereof, their damnation is just</hi> Ro: <hi>3.8.</hi> Therefore <hi>let us not receive the grace of God in vain, 2 Cor. 6.1.2.</hi> for affliction if we make aright use of it, is the greatest sign of Gods love to us, <hi>Heb. 12.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14.</hi> but if when afflicted men will be hardned in their sins, then let them look for a further judgement to come upon them, <hi>Rom. 2.4, 5, 6.</hi> And I tell you plainly, as I have told you a year agone in my Book called the <hi>Eccho,</hi> that the Kingdom which shall be erected here, is not for Drunkards, Swearers, and such as follow those courses of life: Therefore, if you love the <hi>King,</hi> and your own selves, repent speedily, and make your peace with <hi>God:</hi> so shall you have your hearts desire in any lawfull thing.</p>
            <p>They that are of the <hi>Kings</hi> party, blames thē of the <hi>Parlaments</hi> party for their Solemn for swearing of themselves: And they of the <hi>Parlaments</hi> party, blam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s thē of the <hi>Kings</hi> party for their vain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mō swearing. It is true, the <hi>Parlament</hi> party, though they endangered to lose their souls by their swearing yet they got a great deal of mony to boot: but the <hi>Kings</hi> party lose their mony, and have nothing for their swearing therefore they are no way wise in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:114594:44"/> swearing vainly. Hence we may see <hi>both are guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and they might well agree as convicted priso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and however to refrain from Common <hi>Oaths</hi> is an excellent <hi>vertue,</hi> but to keep Solemn <hi>Oaths</hi> is a far more excellent <hi>vertue;</hi> then condemn the sin in either party, but approve of the <hi>vertue,</hi> And let there be a reconciliation between us, if so be <hi>God</hi> will be pacified for our sins past.</p>
            <p>The Presbyterians say, that <hi>Drunkenness is the Root of all evil,</hi> truly it comes very nigh it: but the Apostle saith, that <hi>money is the Root of all evil;</hi> and that the Presbyterians loves so well, that they brought all this evil upon this Land, through the love they had to mony, <hi>1 Tim. 6.9, 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to prove their point, the Presbyterians bring this similitude, one Mr. <hi>Peck</hi> by name at <hi>Christ-church</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> said he, There was a man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der temptation, and he had his choise of <hi>3.</hi> things, The first was, to <hi>kill</hi> his Father: The second was, to <hi>abuse</hi> his Mother: The third was, to be <hi>drunk.</hi> The man having no <hi>Rest,</hi> considering it was a hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous thing for him to <hi>kill</hi> his Father, or to <hi>abuse</hi> Mother, chose rather to be <hi>drunk,</hi> looking upon that as a small sin, in comparison of the others, and he went and made himself <hi>drunk,</hi> but being <hi>drunk</hi> he <hi>abused</hi> his Mother, and his Father going to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him in his humors, he <hi>kill'd</hi> his Father, so be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>drunk</hi> he committed all the <hi>3</hi> Crimes; but <hi>Mr. Peck</hi> did not tell who this man was.</p>
            <p>Therefore I will tell you, this man was Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>John Knox,</hi> he was under <hi>3</hi> Temptations, all these things was in his heart, but he chose to be drunk with the word, <hi>Isa. 29.9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</hi> And being drunk, be abused his mother the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>King Charls</hi> going to save the <hi>Church,</hi> Presbyter <hi>John</hi> kill'd the <hi>King,</hi> and so committed those <hi>3</hi> odious Crimes.</p>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:114594:45"/>
            <p>Thus the antient Fathers Riddle (<hi>which</hi> Peck, <hi>nor no Presbyter never understood</hi>) is opened unto you; Therefore let Presbyter <hi>John first take the beam out of his own eye, and then shall he see clearly the moa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that is in the Protestants cy,</hi> Mat. <hi>7.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</hi> Then shall they be able to see, what is chiefly meant by Drunkenness, Whoredom, Murthering, Swearing, and Sobriety, according to <hi>Scripture</hi>-language.</p>
            <p>There is many of the Kings side, that say to this purpose unto me, Oh that I might but see the King on his throne, the Church florish, and every one have his own again, on condition I should die that day; <hi>Blessed are ye that hunger and thirst after righteousness, for you shall be filled,</hi> Matt. <hi>5.6.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others be, that say, Oh that I might see the King on his Throne, the Church florish, and every man to have his own, that I might have mine also, to keep such a house as I once did, and relieve the poor, as I was to do, but now they come to me, and I cannot help them, <hi>Blessed are ye merciful ones, for ye shall obtain mercy,</hi> Matth. <hi>5.7.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third there is, that say, Oh that I might see the King on his Throne, the Church florish, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to have his own, then should I have mine to make my friends welcome: And to be liberall toward all that I have to do with; <hi>Blessed is the the liberal, for they shall have plenty,</hi> Pro. <hi>22.9.</hi> Isa. <hi>32.5, 6, 7, 8.</hi> God send us truth and peace, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Arise Evans.</signed>
               <dateline>Black-Friers <hi>in Long-alley,</hi>
                  <date>May 30. 1653. or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the vulgar appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension, 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>